<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Patro-scholastiko-dikaiōsis, or, A justification of the fathers and the schoolmen shewing, that they are not self-condemned for denying the positivity of sin. Being an answer to so much of Mr. Tho. Pierce's book, called Autokatakrisis, as doth relate to the foresaid opinion. By Hen: Hickman, fellow of Magdalene Colledge, Oxon.</title>
            <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1911A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43716)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1989:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Patro-scholastiko-dikaiōsis, or, A justification of the fathers and the schoolmen shewing, that they are not self-condemned for denying the positivity of sin. Being an answer to so much of Mr. Tho. Pierce's book, called Autokatakrisis, as doth relate to the foresaid opinion. By Hen: Hickman, fellow of Magdalene Colledge, Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. Lichfield, fot [sic] Joh. Adams, and Edw. Forrest,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Patro-scholastiko-dikaiōsis" and "Autokatakrisis" are in Greek characters on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the St. David's College Library, Lampeter, Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pierce, Thomas, 1622-1691. --  Autokatakrisis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:1"/>
            <p>Πάτρο-σχολαστικο-δικαίωσις, OR, A JUSTIFICATION OF THE FATHERS and SCHOOLMEN: Shewing, <hi>That they are not Self-condemned for denying the Poſitivity of Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Anſwer to ſo much of Mr. <hi>THO. PIERCE</hi>'s Book, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>Αυτοκατάκρισις, as doth relate to the foreſaid Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> HEN: HICKMAN, <hi>Fellow of</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene <hi>Colledge,</hi> Oxon.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Nonnulli citius volunt exagitare quod non intelligunt, quam quaerere ut intelligant: &amp; non fiunt humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les inquiſitores, ſed ſuperbi calumniatores.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. de Tem Serm, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Solent veritatis hoſtes ſuis jactantiis etiam de nihilo theatrum quaerere.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Calv in Mar 9.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Inclamant Puritanos, Puritanos, ſed per Puritano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum latera Orthodoxam vulnerant veritatem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>D Holland referente M. Bolton.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Lichfield,</hi> for <hi>Joh. Adams,</hi> and <hi>Edw. Forreſt.</hi> 1659.</p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:3"/>
            <head>To the reverend and learned the weekely Lecturers at <hi>Brackly.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fathers and Brethren.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou will a little wonder to ſee mee in print, more wonder to ſee mee medling with a ſubject ſomewhat remote from practice, moſt of all wonder to find mee engaging with an adverſary, who drinketh up ſcorning like Water, and knows not how to mention the worthiest man alive, if of a differing judgment, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Nor would you ceaſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, if I ſhould tell you, that the mere importunity of friends (which is now made the common vouchee for publications) did put me upon this undertaking, nay, though <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33604:4"/> hath told us <hi>that a good name is better than a pretious ointment;</hi> yet if Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had contented himſelf to give mee alone ill names, you would never think it any part of my duty, to ſcribble ſo many ſheets in my own vindication: but when as I have found a wanton wit doing by all the honeſt Presbyterians and Puritanes as did the heathen perſecutors by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians, putting them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to beaſts skins, abuſing them with all the odious epithets and aſperſions he could ſcrape together, the one half whereof if they ſhould deſerve, they were not worthy to live, and when as I have heard that ſome are too apt to believe thoſe things real which are the mere chimaera's of his brain, you will not count it an idle expence of time, if I beſtow ſome paines (and very little will ſerve) to ſhew the World that he who is ſo fierce in charging others with blaſphemy, doth maintain an opinion on which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily
<pb facs="tcp:33604:4"/> and unavoideably follows the worſt of blaſphemies Gods being the Author of ſin, and that the privative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of morall evill is not a <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hatched under the wings of a few diſciplinarian zealots;</hi> not <hi>a perfect phantaſie, a mere Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall notion</hi> as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> is pleaſed to call it, fundam. <hi>Pag 178.</hi> But the undoubted opinion of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and of moderne Divines as well <hi>Lutheran</hi> as <hi>Calviniſtical,</hi> yea and that in the way which ſome angry Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines now with extream bitterneſſe call <hi>Calviniſme</hi> the <hi>ancient Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Divines worſhipped the God of their Fathers.</hi> Two Artifices I have obſerved ſome violent Spirits of late to make much uſe of, in order to the drawing away of perſons from the opinions in which they have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated. <hi>1.</hi> to perſwade them that the opinions they have embraced are but the crude indigeſted notions of ſome Presbyterians, ſo Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:33604:5"/> book which ſhould have been called <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> or <hi>Socinus Iuſtificatus,</hi> would bear us in hand that he quarrelleth onely with the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> notion of <hi>Original ſin;</hi> and yet to that tract the Stationer hath unluckily joyned another, in which he labours to give as good an account, and make as fair an Apology for his tenet as he can, to an Eminent Prelate of our own Nation, who can as little digest that Chapter in the <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> as the moſt rigidly Scotized Presbyterian. And I hope none of our old Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants will be caught with ſuch chaffe. A <hi>2.</hi> Stratagem is this, after they have fathered the aſſertions against which they declaime, upon Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his followers, then to Burthen them with ſuch horrible conſequences, as cannot by any true rules of reaſon be deduced from them, as if they were contrary to the <hi>Holineſſe, Mercy, Juſtice of God, as if they introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced fatall neceſſity, and opened a
<pb facs="tcp:33604:5"/> gap to all manner of Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as in the first deſign they do unwittingly befriend the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, by giving the people occaſion to think that they onely are the men, <hi>who will contend for the faith once delivered to the ſaints;</hi> ſo in the latter they do (whether wittingly, or unwittingly they beſt know) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend the Synagogue of Rome; for as <hi>B. Carleton,</hi> ſaith well: <hi>Pag. 62. What greater pleaſure can a man procure to the Enemies of the truth, than to ſpeak evill and odiouſly of thoſe men whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice God hath uſed, and made them excellent inſtruments to make the truth known unto us? Some take it for a ſign of ſuch as are looking towards Popery, when they offer ſuch a ſervice to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, as to ſpeak evill of them who have been the greateſt Enemies to Popery, the greateſt propagators of the truth.</hi> I have took occaſion to
<pb facs="tcp:33604:6"/> as far as my Antagoniſt offered it to make bare both theſe two fallacies, and to that end have ſcarſe made uſe of any teſtimony, but ſuch as he dare not call Presbyterian. If at any time I ſeeme to depart from that meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Spirit, which is required in a Miniſter, I ſhall deſire it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not onely what is fit for mee to ſpeak, but what is meet for him to hear. If I were to mention their fact, who took the reliques of <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr's</hi> wifes carkaſe out of the grave, and after buried them in a dunghill, would you not allow mee to call it, unchriſtian, and inhumane? And ſhall I be permitted to put no vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in my Pen, when I am to write of one, who hath taken the far greater part of our Proteſtant writers out of thoſe beds of honour, in which the Church hath laid them, and made their graves amongſt blaſhpemers are the keeneſt words to keen for a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Bolſec?</hi> an <hi>Engliſh Feuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33604:6"/> And hath not Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf ſuch? Come out of your duſt yee ancient records, and ſhew us if you can, ſince Mr. <hi>Mountagues Appeale,</hi> any peece written by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divine, ſo full of bitter girds, and ſcurrilous gibes, againſt the great inſtruments of our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the late <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are: But I know how hard it is for one who hath been ſo courſely and undecently dealt with as I have been, not to exceed bounds; if you find me ſo to have done, be not ſo cruelly mercifull as not to call me to repentance. And for your ſelves, <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men, the Lord is at</hi> hand. The reproaches where with you are reproached, are no other than ſuch as the old Puritanes <hi>(of whom the world was not worthy)</hi> were exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with. Let me alſo mind you of the grave, and ſeaſonable counſell, which <hi>Galba</hi> gave to <hi>Piſo. Nero a peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
<pb facs="tcp:33604:7"/> quoque deſiderabitur, mihi &amp; tibi providendum eſt, ne etiam à bonis deſideretur:</hi> The Epiſcopal go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, as it was exerciſed in your County, will be deſired by the bad, let not the good wiſh it reſtored alſo, for any Church Governement is better than no Church Government, a promiſcuous admiſſion to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is more deſireable than a totall diſuſe of that moſt bleſſed ordinance. If you will but put in practice the rules you pitched upon when you were firſt about to enter into an aſſociation with your Brethren, you ſhall as little need to fear the ſpleen of him who calleth your ordinations Prankes, as the clamour of thoſe who call your Churches <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> That the word of the Lord may run and be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified among you: <hi>That God would open unto you a door of utterance, to ſpeak the Myſtery of Chriſt,</hi> for which you endure contradiction of
<pb facs="tcp:33604:7"/> ſinners, and that when your work is done in this life you may <hi>enter into your Maſters glory</hi> is the prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthieſt of your fellow labourers</hi> H. Hickman.</signed>
               <dateline>Magd. Colledg.
<date>Nov. <hi>22<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1658.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:8"/>
            <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I never ſaw Mr. <hi>Peirce</hi> his face, yet ſo much have I been taken with that rich vein of Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, which runnes through all his Writings falling under my eye, that thoſe few friends, in whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acquaintance wee meet, will teſtifie, I have not mentioned his name without thoſe prefaces of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which are due to a Scholar: Nor hath his debaſing mee to the dunghill of Doltiſme, put me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any temptation to detract from the credit and reputation which he hath acquired unto himſelf among
<pb facs="tcp:33604:9"/> our young Gallants, by putting the good Greek and Latin of the old Philoſophers into as good Engliſh, is his Practicals, by abuſing Mr. <hi>Bar.</hi> with Drollery, as handſome as ever drop'd from the Pen of <hi>Ben. Johnſon</hi> in his Polemicals. But as Bees are ſometimes drowned in their Honey, ſo is his Logick in his Rhetorick; the body of his Proofs being as poor, and lean, as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh of his words, and margin glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; his ſtuffe as meane, as his dreſſing rich. And therefore I reckon him many waies unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in chooſing the tremendous myſtery of Reprobation for his firſt publick Eſſay. <hi>Eccius</hi> indeed in his <hi>Chryſopaſ.</hi> where he entreateth concerning Reprobation, ſaith, he did chooſe it as an idoneous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>in quo juveniles calores exerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</hi> But that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> a perſon, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to be of that party by whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:33604:9"/> means a declaration was procured, injoyning ſilence in theſe points, to be an admirer of Biſhop <hi>Montague,</hi> who in his firſt Viſitation made this one Article of Enquiry; <hi>Doth your Miniſter commonly, or on ſet purpoſe, in his popular Sermons, fall upon thoſe much diſputed, and little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood Doctrines, of Gods eternall Predeſtination, of Election preceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, of Reprobation irreſpective without ſinne fore-ſeen, of Free-will, of Perſeverance, and not falling from Grace, points obſcure, unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, unfordable, untractable, at which that great Apoſtle ſtood at gaze, with, O the height, and depth of the riches of the wiſdom and knowledge of God, how unſearchable are his judgements and his wayes paſt finding out.</hi> Rom. 11.31. That Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſhould ſport his fancy in theſe troubled waters, wherein ſo many have made ſhip-wrack of faith and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would ſeem ſtrange to me:
<pb facs="tcp:33604:10"/> But that I am fallen into an Age in which I have learned to admire nothing; not ſo much from any knowledge I have attained unto of the cauſes of things, as from the multitude of ſtrange effects.</p>
            <p>But, that 2ly; I had long ſince learned, that the foreſaid Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was never intended to bee a two edged Sword, was never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured out of any charitable deſign, to ſettle the Peace of the Church, but out of a politick deſigne, to ſtop the mouthes of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, who were ſure to be cenſured, if they at any time declared their minds, whilſt the new upſtart Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians were ſuffered to Preach and Print their Heterodox notions with out any controule: leſt in this I ſhould be ſuſpected of partiality, or falſhood, I will quote the words of the moſt Noble Lord <hi>Faulkland,</hi> in his Speech to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons printed, Anno 1641. For
<pb facs="tcp:33604:10"/> 
               <hi>Thom. Walkeley,</hi> Pag. 5, 6. <hi>Mr.</hi> Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>in this they have abuſed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty as well as his people; for when he had with great wiſdome ſilenced on both parts thoſe opinions, which have often tormented the Church, and have, and will all way trouble the Schooles, they made uſe of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to tye up one ſide, and let the other looſe; whereas they ought either in diſcretion to have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually reſtrained, or in juſtice to have been equally tolerated, and it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that the party to which they gave this licence was that, whoſe Doctrine, though it were not contrary to Law, was contrary to cuſtome, and for a long while in this Kingdome was, no ofter preached than recanted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> have for the time paſt (what he tells us for the future he reſolves) beſtowed onely his times of <hi>Leiſure</hi> and <hi>diverſion</hi> upon theſe diſputes, he is the more excuſeable: But if whileſt he hath <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:33604:11"/> ſtones at Mr. <hi>Bar.</hi> head, his Children have wanted their bread, or have been fain to take it divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them by a more unskillfull hand then his own: Then hath he put ſomething on his <hi>doomeſday booke,</hi> which I wiſh he may have time to take off by repentance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goe away and ſhall be ſeen no more: and let him take this counſell from one (who though conſtrained to diſſent from his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, is a cordial friend to his Perſon) quickly to <hi>kiſſe the Son</hi> who muſt needs be offended with him for his hard ſpeeches uſed againſt thoſe pretious Divines beyond the Seas, ſcarſe to be <hi>equalled</hi> by any now a live, or to be <hi>excelled</hi> by thoſe in any <hi>Calendar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So little do I delight to have my fingers in the fire of contention that have meddled with nothing in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. but what I my ſelf am, at leaſt by him thought, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb facs="tcp:33604:11"/> in. Whether I be <hi>ſupra,</hi> or <hi>ſublapſarian,</hi> or neither in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of reprobation, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies depending thereon no one knows, or can pretend to know, from any thing they have heard me ſay in the Pulpit, and if I have not thought meet to make theſe things a Pulpit buſineſſe, why ſhould I declare my minde about them from the preſſe? If my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion be <hi>in ſome particulars ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular,</hi> then perhaps it may be my duty to <hi>have my knowledge to my ſelf;</hi> if in all things I agree with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Calviniſtical perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I muſt then, before I write one, conſider twice whether I can ſay any thing that others have not ſaid before in moſt full and ample manner; for he had need be very prodigal of his credit, who in ſuch a curious and inquiſitive age as this will ſerve up his Reader with onely a diſh of twenty times ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:33604:12"/> coleworts. Yet becauſe I am brought upon the ſtage, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath thought meet to blaſt me with the utmoſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his hatred, the title of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſt</hi> and <hi>Puritan,</hi> and becauſe I find ſome to make uſe of this <hi>Jvy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh</hi> to tole in <hi>cuſtomers,</hi> that they <hi>are obedient Sons of the Chuch of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> I ſhall beg thy patience (good Reader) whileſt I ſhew that not the Remonſtrant, but the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra-remonſtrant opinion hath been the Doctrine of the <hi>Reformed Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and that the <hi>Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> of <hi>Arminianiſme</hi> with us, is no older than Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Mountague,</hi> who are but of <hi>yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in compariſon:</hi> But do not theſe men much forget themſelves whileſt they appeale to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> Was it not the Church of England that in her 35th. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle did legitimate the books of homilies, and are not ſuch words to
<pb facs="tcp:33604:12"/> be found in the homily againſt the <hi>Peril</hi> of <hi>Idolatry: The image of God Father, Son, or Holy Ghoſt, either ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, or the images of the Trinity, be by the Scriptures expreſſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, and condemned, as appears by theſe places, Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Vide ibidem plura.</hi> How then was the late Arcſhbiſhop an obedient Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> who put Mr. <hi>Sherlfield</hi> a Bencher of Linc. Inne, and Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Sarum</hi> to ſo much coſt, and a diſgracefull acknowledgment of his fault, and cauſed him to be bound to his good behaviour, <hi>for taking down a glaſſe Window, in which there were made no leſſe then</hi> 7. <hi>pictures of God the Father in forme of a little old man, clad in a blew and red coat, with a Pouch by his ſide about the bigneſſe of a Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet.</hi> Yea I have heard it from a Gentleman of good repute <hi>that the Archbiſhop then juſtified the Pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33604:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33604:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33604:14"/> of God the Father, in forme of an old man, out of that place of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, where God is called the ancient of dayes.</hi> Nay Biſhop <hi>Lindſey,</hi> one of the Archbiſhops great Creatures was not aſhamed to ſay? <hi>That none but ignorant Calviniſt Biſhops did put down Altars at the beginning of the Reformation; and that they were worſe then Ieſuites: that he was much offended with the Homily's againſt the Perill of Idolatry, againſt ſetting up of images in Churches; that he would have theſe Homilies put out of the Homily book, &amp; wondred why they were ſuffered to continue in it ſo long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, who by her Lords Spiritual in the upper houſe, and her whole convocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the Act for the ſubſidy of the Clergy? 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Iacobi</hi> defined the <hi>Pope to be the</hi> Antichriſt, was it not Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> poſitive opinion that the Pope is <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> was it not Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgifts,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement
<pb facs="tcp:33604:14"/> aſſertion 1569. <hi>Papa eſt ille</hi> Antichriſtus: was not this alſo poſitively aſſerted by Archbiſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and proved by King <hi>Iames,</hi> and muſt they now be called the onely obedient Sons of our, Church who ſtudy by all their Learning to take off that ignominious name from the Pope, and faſten it upon I know not whom?</p>
            <p>Was it not the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland who in her 9th. Article, ſpeaks ſo plainly concerning Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin, <hi>That it ſtandeth not in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of</hi> Adam, <hi>as the Pelagians do vainely talke, but is the fault and corruption of the nature of every man, that naturally is engendred of the off-ſpring of</hi> Adam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And muſt he now that ſet forth the <hi>unum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium,</hi> then whom <hi>Pelagius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf could not be more Pelagian, be reſorted unto and reputed as an Oracle by thoſe who glory in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then in beeing old <hi>Eliz:
<pb facs="tcp:33604:15"/> Proteſtants.</hi> O that thoſe who have any zeal for the Religion ſealed by the blood of our Martyrs, defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the pens of our Divines, the ſwords of our Soldiers, eſtabliſhed by the Law of our Nation would conſider what I write: But theſe are <hi>Parerga'es</hi> to our grand deſign, which was to find out the opinion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters debated betwixt the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants, and Contra remonſtrants: for the carrying on whereof, it will not be amiſſe to conſider our Church in a twofold capacity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our general Reformation; &amp; after it. Before the general Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in whom ſhould we ſeeke our Church but in our Martyrs and confeſſors? who did witneſſe againſt the Synagogue of Sathan, what were the opinions of <hi>Wichlief,</hi> we can ſcarce find but in the Hiſtory of Papiſts, who would be ſure to make him as odious as they could tell
<pb facs="tcp:33604:15"/> how to draw him, but by their lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to his charge, <hi>that he brought in fatal neceſſity,</hi> that he <hi>made God the author of ſin,</hi> we may make a probable gheſſe that there was no diſagreement betwixt him and Mr. <hi>Iohn Calvin.</hi> For the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight wee have through ſpecial providence ſome workes of Mr <hi>William Tyndall,</hi> Mr, <hi>Iohn Frith,</hi> Mr. Dr. <hi>Barnes</hi> preſerved, which are all bound up together, and put forth by <hi>Iohn Day:</hi> 1563: Mr. <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> (than whom <hi>Magd. Coll.</hi> hath ſcarce ever had, a member, of whom ſhe may more juſtly boaſt) putting a large preface, in which he ſtileth them the <hi>cheife ring-leaders of the Church of England.</hi> How point blank they ſpeake for the things that now are called Calviniſtical errors, may be ſeen with a little labour, if any one will looke upon the index, though he that will read the book it ſelfe once over for my ſake, will
<pb facs="tcp:33604:16"/> read it over twice for his owne. Come we to the more conſpicuous eſtate of our Church, when Kings and Queens have vouchſafed to be nurſing Fathers and Mothers to it, when ſhe hath ſpoken to her members by the 39. Art. Homilies, Liturgies, Catechiſmes, theſe we will conſult that we may be ſure, if it be poſſible to know her mind. The Articles were firſt agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Convocation holden in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt 1552. confirmed and repromulgated, Anno 1562. ratified by King <hi>Iames,</hi> 1604. and by King <hi>Charles,</hi> 1628. Some little variation there is in the ſeveral editions of them, about which I mind not to trouble my ſelf, ſeeing the 17th Article is the ſame in all, the words are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: <hi>Predeſtination to life, is the everlaſting purpoſe of God, whereby before the foundation of the World laid, he hath constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:33604:16"/> decreed by his counſel ſecret to us, to deliver from curſe and damnation, thoſe whom he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in Chriſt out of mankind, and to bring them by Chriſt to everlaſting ſalvation, as veſſels made to honour: wherefore they which be endued with ſo excellent a benefit of God, be call'd according to Gods purpoſe, by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, working in due ſeaſon; they, through grace obey the calling; they be juſtified freely; they be made ſons of God by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption; they be made like the image of his onely begotten Son Ieſus Chriſt; they walk religiouſly in good workes, and at length by Gods mercy they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to everlaſting felicity, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can any one that reads the common prayer booke with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced mind chooſe but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve divers paſſages that manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make for a perſonall, eternall election. That which may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of our Homilies I will not tranſcribe, ſeeing the booke is
<pb facs="tcp:33604:17"/> commonly to be had: Let me only minde thoſe, who are not wont much to deal in any books but our new Pamplets, of a Catechiſme ſet forth by Authority for all Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters to teach in King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. daies, the very year after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the publick Articles, the King prefixed his royal Epiſtle, wherein he commands and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all Schoolmaſters whatſoever within his Dominions, as they did reverence his Authority, and as they would avoyd his royal diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to teach this Catechiſme dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and carefully, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In that Catechiſme, how doe Maſter and Scholar plainly declare themſelves to be no friends to any of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> contends for?</p>
            <p>If this Book be not at hand, let the Bible printed by <hi>Rob. Barker, Anno</hi> 1607. be conſulted, and at the end of the Old Teſtament, there
<pb facs="tcp:33604:17"/> will be found certain Queſtions and Anſwers touching the Doctrine of Predeſtination, which are as full and punctual againſt Arminianiſme as may be.</p>
            <p>But leſt all this ſhould not bee thought evidence ſufficient, we will produce our Arguments to prove the Church of <hi>England</hi> not to bee Arminian; and if not Arminian, much leſſe could ſhe account Anti-arminianiſm Blaſphemy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who were the Compoſers of our 39 Articles? were they not all the Diſciples and Auditors of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr?</hi> or at leaſt ſuch as held conſent with them in Doctrine? Dr. <hi>Alexander Nowel</hi> was Prolocutor of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in the time of Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> And whether he had any Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Arminians, let his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme ſpeak, I mean the Engliſh one, dedicated to the two Archbiſh. <hi>To the Church doe all they properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long,
<pb facs="tcp:33604:18"/> as many as do truly fear, honour, and call upon God, altogether apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their minds to live holily and godly, and which putting all their truſt in God, do moſt aſſuredly look for the bleſſedneſſe of eternall life, they that be ſtedfast, ſtable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in this faith, were choſen, and appointed, and (as we term it) prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to this ſo great felicity,</hi> pag. 44. <hi>and</hi> (paulo poſt) <hi>the Chuch is the body of the Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale;</hi> i. e. <hi>the univerſal number and fellowſhip of the faithfull, whom God through Chriſt, hath before all begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time appointed to everlaſting life.</hi> Shall we think that he, and others engaged with him in the ſame <hi>Convocation,</hi> were ſo ignorant, that they underſtood not what they put into the Articles? or ſo infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, as to put in things that were quite contrary to their own judgement?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Church of <hi>England</hi> did
<pb facs="tcp:33604:18"/> conſent to the opinions commonly called Arminian, how came ſhe to diſpoſe of her places of greateſt influence and truſt, to ſuch as were of a contrary perſwaſion? no places in our Church are more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for leavening the Clergy than the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the two Chaires in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, both theſe have been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied by thoſe who deteſted Arminianiſme as the ſhadow of death. <hi>Parker, Grindall, Whitgift, Bancroft, Abbot,</hi> are all known; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the time of Biſhop <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft,</hi> came forth the book, called, <hi>The Faith, Religion, Doctrine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in the Realm of England, and Dominions thereof;</hi> ſaid in the Title page <hi>to be peruſed, and by the lawful authority of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>allowed to be made publick.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> or any one for him name the Dr. of the Chaire in <hi>Oxon,</hi> that did not <hi>totis viribus,</hi> oppoſe ſuch a Platform
<pb facs="tcp:33604:19"/> of Gods Decrees as men would faign obtrude upon us now. In <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ambridge indeed we may find one Dr. <hi>Overall,</hi> who may bee ſuſpected a little to Arminianiſe, but his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is diſliked by Mr. <hi>Playfer</hi> in his <hi>Apello Evangelium,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not that which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſtickleth for. In the Conference at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, he did declare himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the totall, or finall falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of Gods elect: And would Mr. <hi>P.</hi> but come over to us in the point of Election, &amp; Gods invincible work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the hearts of his choſen ones, we ſhould ſoon agree, or elſe very eaſily bear with one another in our differences.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> go the way that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath taught him, how came it to paſſe, that as many as trod the Arminian path, were wont to be ſuppreſſed &amp; cenſured, ſo ſoon as they beganne to diſcover themſelves? Who is ſuch a ſtranger
<pb facs="tcp:33604:19"/> in the Hiſtory of the Univerſity, that hath not heard of <hi>Barrets</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, made in the Univerſity Church, 10. of <hi>May</hi> 1595? And theſe are the words of the Order, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing him that penalty, <hi>Habitâ maturâ deliberatione, nec non viſis &amp; diligenter examinatis poſitionibus praedictis, quia manifeſto conſtabat poſitiones praedictas errorem &amp; falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem in ſe continere, nec non aperte repugnare religioni in Eccleſia Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canâ receptae ac ſtabilitae, ideo judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt, &amp;c.</hi> See more in Mr. <hi>Th. Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Peter Baro</hi>'s Arminianiſme coſt him the loſs of his place, and which was worſt, loſt him the Affections of the Univerſity. Mr. <hi>Edward Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> a fine Critick, preached a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before King <hi>Iames</hi> at <hi>Royſton,</hi> taking for his Text, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.6. <hi>That which is born of the fleſh is fleſh:</hi> hence he endeavoured to prove, that the Commiſſion of any <hi>great ſinne</hi> doth extinguiſh <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:33604:20"/> the time in man. Hee added alſo, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſeventh Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſpake not of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as an <hi>Apostle</hi> and <hi>Regenerate,</hi> but <hi>ſub ſtatu legis.</hi> Hereat his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty took (&amp; publickly expreſſed) great diſtaſte; becauſe <hi>Arminius</hi> had lately been blamed for extrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the like expoſition out of the Works of <hi>Faustus Socinus;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hee ſent to the <hi>two Profeſſors</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi> for their judgement herein, who proved, and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the place, <hi>ad Rom.</hi> 7. to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of a <hi>Regenerate man,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> his later o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion In his <hi>Retractations;</hi> and the <hi>Preacher</hi> was enjoyned a <hi>publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation</hi> before the <hi>King;</hi> which was performed accordingly.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mountagues</hi> Appeale had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt been ſtrangled in the womb by Archbiſh. <hi>Abbot.</hi> When it ſaw light, how exceedingly it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliked, may appear by the ſeveral
<pb facs="tcp:33604:20"/> Anſwers made to it by Biſh. <hi>Carle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Dean <hi>Sutliffe,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Yates,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wooton,</hi> all Epiſcopal: Presbyt. Mr. <hi>Francis Rouſe:</hi> Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. Mr. <hi>Henry Burton.</hi> Nor doe his Reſpondents object any thing more than his diſſent from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> He was cenſured for it by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Mr. <hi>Rim</hi> from the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Religion made this Report to the Houſe of Commons, <hi>April</hi> 18. 1626. <hi>That hee had diſturbed the peace of the Church, by publiſhing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines contrary to the Articles of the Church of England, and the Book of Homilies; that the whole frame and ſcope of the booke was to diſcourage the well affected in Religion from the true Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church, and to encline them, and as much as in him lay, to reconcile them to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Let mee here inſert an Order made by the Houſe of Commons, 28 <hi>Ian.</hi> 1628. after a large Debate: <hi>We the Commons now aſſembled in
<pb facs="tcp:33604:21"/> Parliament, do claim, profeſs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow for truth, the ſenſe of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Religion, which were eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Parliament,</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz. which by the publick Acts of the Church of England, and the general and currant expoſition of the Writers of our Church, have been delivered to us; and we reject the ſenſe of the Ieſuites and Arminians, and all others wherein they differ from us.</hi> If any one ſhall be deſirous to know why we meet with no cenſures of Arminianiſme in <hi>Oxon?</hi> the anſwer wil be, that thi<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was not becauſe ſhe had leſſe zeal<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt that error than her Siſter<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but becauſe her members either were free from it, or elſe kept it to themſelves. Yet I could tell him o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Howſons</hi> ſuſpenſion for flurtin<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at Mr. <hi>Iohn Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How comes it to paſs, tha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe who now follow <hi>Arminius,</hi> di<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heretofore follow Mr. <hi>Calvin?</hi> D<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iacksons</hi> Queſtions <hi>in veſper:</hi> 162<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were, <hi>An peccatum originale liberum
<pb facs="tcp:33604:21"/> arbitrium in Adamo, &amp; ipſius poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris penitus extinxit?</hi> Affirm. <hi>An voluntas hominis lapſi ſic libera quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad actum converſionis ad Deum?</hi> Neg. And whoſe theſe were 1627. <hi>An praedeſtinatio ad ſalutem ſit prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter praeviſam fidem?</hi> Neg. <hi>An praedestinatio ad ſalutem ſit mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis?</hi> Neg. <hi>An gratia ad ſalutem ſufficiens concedatur omnibus?</hi> Neg. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> knows, if he knows who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him a Demy. Nay he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf confeſſeth, that he holdeth not the ſame opinions that he did when he firſt commenced Mr. What did not the Parents, Maſters, Tutors of theſe perſons know what the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Engl.</hi> was? or were they ſome ſchiſmatical Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans who inſtructed them in a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contrary to what is eſtabliſht by Law? I hope they will not ſo blemiſh their education; yet doe they not ſtrangely blemiſh the Church her ſelfe? For if ſhee did verily apprehend theſe <hi>Geneva</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb facs="tcp:33604:22"/> to be ſo contrary to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe, why hath ſhee not in ſome Convocation declared the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſneſſe of theſe tenents, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her Sonnes againſt ſuch Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms and Syſtems of Divinity as do contain them? Why hath the <hi>Practice of Pietie, Perkins his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Balls Catechiſme,</hi> with divers others been ſo often printed?</p>
            <p n="5">5. If the Church be ſo cordially for Arminianiſme, how came it to paſs that King <hi>Iames</hi> ſhould bee ſo very ſolicitous to have it weeded out in other Churches? Did he not put the States upon calling an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to condemn <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> and his party? Did he not ſend ſome of his Divines of ſingular Piety and parts to ſit in that Aſſembly? char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them not to agree to any thing contrary to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet rewarding them at their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, when they had ſuffraged to the <hi>contra remonſtrants.</hi> Did not he
<pb facs="tcp:33604:22"/> exclaim againſt the impudence of <hi>Bertius,</hi> for ſaying that his Doctrine of the Apoſtaſie of Saints was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Doctrine of our Church? Doe but obſerve how Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſtrives to get out of your hand, though you think you have him faſt: <hi>Div. Puri.</hi> p. 6, 7. <hi>Although King Iames in his younger yeares had imbibed and ſuckt in, even before hee was aware, that Presbyterian opinion of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevizing, Scotiſh Kirk (which no man living will think ſtrange, who knows the place of his birth &amp; his education) yet in riper and wiſer years, he found ſo great reaſon to retract and abjure his former error, that he readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of Biſhop</hi> Mountagues <hi>Appeal, and commanded it to be printed, and to be dedicated alſo unto his royal ſelf, when even this was the Doctrine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed for, that the children of God may fall away, according to the tenour of our ſixteenth Article, which the King perceiving to be the words and mind of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and
<pb facs="tcp:33604:23"/> that</hi> Bertius <hi>had diſcerned it a great deal ſooner than himſelfe, he did not think it below him to grow in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; wiſdom as well as yeares.</hi> The very mentioning of B. <hi>Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> makes him talk like a Dictator rather than an Hiſtorian. B. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi> ſaith in his Appeale, leſt the <hi>Lambeth</hi> Articles ſhould too much ſtand in his way, <hi>that they were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards forbidden by publick autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Tho. Fuller,</hi> Book 9. p. 231. makes himſelf a little merry with the Learned man; <hi>When, where, and by whom this prohibition was made, he is not pleaſed to tell us: and ſtrange it is, that a publick Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be whiſpered ſo ſoftly, that this author alone ſhould hear it, and none other to my knowledge take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof.</hi> Such another Winter tale hath Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> told us: King <hi>Iames</hi> changed his judgment: when, or where? how many monthes or years before his death? of theſe not a tittle. Doth he think that ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb facs="tcp:33604:23"/> a change will bee believed without very ſtrong proofs? I can prove that not above a month be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dyed, giving directions and inſtructions to two Divines, having occaſion to touch upon the treatiſes of St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> that are extant in the 7. Tome, he ſtiled them. S. <hi>Auguſtins Polemical Tracts againſt the Hereticks that agree with our Arminians, and preſently calling to minde their proper name, termed thoſe Hereticks Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Vid. Feat. Parallels.</hi> Now though ſome people, who vvill be prating about vvhat concerns them not, do talk parilouſly about ſome poyſon given to the King, not long before his death, yet that the poyſon vvas the Arminian errors, I never heard or dreamed. That the Divines em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed at that venerable Synod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver changed their mind, is beyond all doubt. Hear Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> in their Letters to one another. Biſhop <hi>Hall:</hi> 
               <q>Yea as if this calumny was not enough,
<pb facs="tcp:33604:24"/> there want not thoſe whoſe ſecret whiſperings caſt upon me the foul aſperſions of another ſect, whoſe name is as much hated, as little underſtood. My Lord, you know I had a place with you (though unworthy) in that famous Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> where (however ſickneſs bereaved me of the honour of a concluſive ſubſcription) yet your Lordſhip heard mee with equall vehemence to the reſt crying downe the unreaſonableneſſe of that way. I am ſtil the ſame man, and ſhall live and die in the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of that reverend Synod, &amp; doe confidently avow, that thoſe other oppoſed opinions, cannot ſtand with the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q> Biſhop <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> replyeth. <q>As for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion of Arminianiſme, I can teſtifie, that in our joint employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> you were as farre from it as my ſelfe. And I know that no man can em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb facs="tcp:33604:24"/> it, in the Doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination and grace, but he muſt firſt deſert the Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon by the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: nor in the point of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, but he muſt vary from the common Tenet and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion of our beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctors in the Engliſh Church</q>, <hi>Mentis aureae verba bracteata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Notwithſtanding all this, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is plainly ſaid that we may fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from grace received Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle 16. As will appear if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the 16<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Article, with the firſt part of the homily touching fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away from God, <hi>Pag.</hi> 54.57. With the forme of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> with the Catechiſme, and all with the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court. Pag.</hi> 29, 30, 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All theſe have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by every one of thoſe 7. wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that undertook the anſwer to
<pb facs="tcp:33604:25"/> Mr. <hi>Mountagues</hi> appeal, &amp; yet they never thought it incumbent upon them to alter their minds Mr. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi> ſaith both in his Gag &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, that our Church hath left this undecided; and in the conference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> I find Dr. <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> moving that the words total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and finally might be added for explication of the Article, and that the Lambeth Articles might be in ſerted. The King then unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Lambeth Articles, thought not meet to put them in: But liked it well enough in his Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that they took them into their confeſſion, Dr. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall</hi> ſaid ſomething touching an opinion of his, about which he had been queſtioned by ſome, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that the elect do never fall away totally, or finally. The Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> ſaid he knew, there were ſome that did make an ill uſe of the decrees; But had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:33604:25"/> the conference agreed to the Lambeth Articles, and after the conference when he was Archb. his Chaplain with his good liking and approbation publiſhed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and <hi>Analyſis</hi> of our <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> in which he gives the <hi>Calviniſt</hi> as fair <hi>quarter</hi> as could be wiſhed. And now I would faing know why I am ſent to the conference at <hi>Hampton-Court?</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> had I warrant you read Artic. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, forme of Baptiſm, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could ſcarce tell how <hi>to ſpeak not judiciouſly</hi> we will conſult him, the rather becauſe it ſeems this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was by <hi>the late King commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his Children as an antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poiſon of Popery.</hi> Diſc. of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifi. <hi>p.</hi> 506. <hi>As Chriſt beeing raiſed from the dead, dyeth no more, death hath no more power over him: So the juſtified man beeing allyed to God in Ieſus Christ our Lord, doth as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily from that time forward all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:33604:26"/> live, as Chriſt by whom he hath life liveth allway. I might if I had not other where largely done it allready, ſhew by many and ſundry, manifeſt and cleer proofs, how the motions and operations of this life, are ſometimes ſo in diſcerneable, and ſo ſecret, that they ſeem ſtone dead, who are notwithstanding ſtill alive unto God in Chriſt. For as long as that abideth in us, which animateth, quickeneth, and giveth life, ſo long we live and we know that the cauſe of our faith abideth in us for ever. If Chriſt the Fountain of life, may flit and leave the habitation, where once he dwelleth, what ſhall become of his promiſe I am with you to the end of the World? If the ſeed of God which containeth Christ, may be firſt concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved &amp; then caſt out how doth St.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>terme it immortall? How doth St.</hi> John <hi>affirme it abideth? If the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is given to cheriſh, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſeed of life, may be given
<pb facs="tcp:33604:26"/> and taken away how is it the earneſt of our in heritance untill redemption. Anno</hi> 1625. one Mr. <hi>Damport,</hi> did anſwer on this Queſtion, <hi>An renati poſſint totaliter &amp; finaliter excidere à gratiâ.</hi> His opponent one Mr. <hi>Palmer</hi> of Lincolne Colledge ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, out of Mr. <hi>Mountagues</hi> appeal the Article of our Church, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, the book of Common prayer, the Dr. of the <hi>Chair handled</hi> the Appellator <hi>ſhrewdly,</hi> ſaying he was <hi>Merus Grammaticus,</hi> a fellow that ſtudied <hi>Phraſes</hi> more than <hi>Matter.</hi> that he underſtood neither the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles;</hi> nor the <hi>Homilies,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>perverted</hi> both.</p>
            <p>And what thinkes Mr. <hi>P.</hi> of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxon?</hi> did not ſhee know the opinions of the Church of England? or would ſhe countenance any thing that had ſo much as the appearance of contrariety to our Church? How came it then to paſſe that her congregations appointed
<pb facs="tcp:33604:27"/> queſtions to be diſputed of at the publick acts, in which are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt confluence of the of Sons of <hi>Levi.</hi> That proceeders maintained in a Calviniſtical way? How many are now alive that can remember this Queſtion, <hi>an ex Doctrina reformatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſequatur Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe autore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccati: held Neg.</hi> And maintained to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the hearers, the Arminian Doctors, mean while ſhewing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rather angry, than able op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents. Let any one who que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioneth the truth of what I now ſay, conſult the Act Papers that are printed as often as thoſe Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſolemnities are celebrated, What ſhould I ſay more, we know when Arminianiſme began, &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe wings it was ſheltered, viz. the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Buck.</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> of whom the firſt had ſo much of an <hi>Herod</hi> in him, as would not have ſuffered him ſo long to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue friendſhip with the latter, if
<pb facs="tcp:33604:27"/> he had not had too little of a <hi>St. Ioh. Baptiſt,</hi> whileſt they did rule, not before, nor ſince, paſſages in books againſt Arminianiſme, were blotted out, reflections in Sermons upon Remonſtrants were diſliked, by Biſhop <hi>Lauds</hi> meanes, Dr. <hi>Downhams</hi> book againſt the <hi>Totall &amp; finall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſy of the ſaints from grace,</hi> was called in, in his dayes Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> of <hi>Mag. H.</hi> Mr. <hi>Thorn</hi> of <hi>Baliol,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> of Exeter, were cenſured; but let it be obſerved that the ground of the Cenſure was not their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preached any thing contrary to the Doctrine of the Church, (which is the forme of the cenſure poſſed upon Arminians by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proteſtants) but onely their going againſt the <hi>Kings Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which determined nothing, but onely injoyned ſilence in theſe points. Now I hope the Church did not live and dye with <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> Nay their flouriſhing was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying
<pb facs="tcp:33604:28"/> and languiſhing of Church and State too, nor could either body vell recover but by ſpewing out ſuch evill inſtruments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> The Church of England is for univerſal redemption the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts that are Antiarminian are againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> indeed is hugely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that it we grant him univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall redemption the cauſe is yeelded to him: But I am all moſt as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that to grant him univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall redemption is to grant him juſt nothing at all, for what though Chriſt did ſo far die for all as to procure a ſalvation for all, upon the conditions of faith and repentance, what's this to the abſoluteneſſe of Gods decrees, or to the inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of converting grace, or to the certain infallible perſeverance of Gods elect after converſion. King <hi>Iames</hi> underſtood theſe controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies far better then either Mr. <hi>P.</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:33604:28"/> 
               <hi>I.</hi> and yet he even at that very time when he ſent his Divines to the Synod of Dort, to determine againſt the Arminianiſme that was then growing in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, gave it them in charge not to deny that Chriſt died for all, as I my ſelf was told by Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> the firſt time I had the happineſſe to have any perſonall diſcourſe with him; who alſo further then told me, that he gave in his own judgement to Dr. <hi>Davenant</hi> for univerſall redemption, but withall added, that there were a certaine number upon whom God abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſed to beſtow his Spirit, taking away the heart of ſtone and giving them an heart of fleſh, and we know that Dr. <hi>Davenant,</hi> in that very diſſertation, in which one concluſion is, <hi>Mors ſive paſſio Chriſti, ut univerſalis cauſa ſalutis humanae deum patrem, ipſo facto oblationis ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuus reddit placatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reconciliatum
<pb facs="tcp:33604:29"/> humano generi, ut vere nunc dicatur paratus quemvis hominem in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam recipere, ſimulac in Chriſtum crediderit; neminem tamen ſaltem ex adultis praedicta Chriſti mors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit in ſtatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gratiae actualis reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liationis, ſive ſalutis, antequam credat.</hi> Hath two more extreamly oppoſite to his darling notions, <hi>Conc:</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">a.</hi> 
               <hi>Poſitâ Chriſti morte omnibus homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus applicabili ſub conditione fidei, ſtat cum bonitate &amp; justitia Divina ſuppeditare vel negare, ſive nationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſive ſingularibus hominibus, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia applicationis id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> pro bene pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cito voluntatis ſue, non pro diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate voluntatis humanae: <hi>&amp; p.</hi> 88. <hi>Mors Chriſti, ex ſpeciali intentione Dei patris illud ſacrificium ab aeterno ordinantis &amp; acceptantis, Chriſtique illud idem in plenitudine temporis deo patri offerentis, deſtinata fuit certis quibuſdam hominibus (quos electos Scriptura vocat) iiſdemque ſolis ut efficaciter &amp; infallibiliter applicanda
<pb facs="tcp:33604:29"/> ad aeternae vitae conſecutionem.</hi> The Comment upon this <hi>Theſis</hi> hee thus begins; <hi>Hanc Theſin opponimus Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniorum errori, quem</hi> Grevinchovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>ſtabilire conatur, diſſer: de morte Chriſti,</hi> p. 7. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi docet Deum tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem Filium ſuum, intendiſſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trationem reconciliationis omnibus et ſingulis communem, applicationem vero ejuſdem impetratae nemini mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium abſolute voluiſſe.</hi> If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> cannot ſwallow theſe two laſt, let him anſwer the Doctors arguments, and count me as much engaged to defend them, as if I my ſelfe had made them. If he can digeſt them, let him know that I have no quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with him about the former, which would never have found ſo many adverſaries among Calviniſts, if the Arminians had ſtated it ſo clearly, &amp; proved it by ſo good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as the Rev. Profeſſor hath don. But what do I talk of agreeing with ſuch a man as Mr. <hi>P?</hi> who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:33604:30"/> than not fight, will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend with his own ſhadow. Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> a bird of the ſame feather, who alſo took his flight from the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane,</hi> will needs have Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the point of univerſal redemption; mark his proof, <hi>p.</hi> 102. <hi>The Church of England doth maintain an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Redemption of all mankind, by the death and ſufferings of our Saviour.</hi> Well, and ſo doth the deceaſed Primate, <hi>p.</hi> 103. <hi>We think not that all mankind is ſo perfectly reconciled to Almighty God, as to be really and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcharged from all their ſinns, before they beleeve, but that they are ſo far reconciled unto him, as to be capable of the remiſſion of their ſins, in caſe they doe not want that faith in their common Saviour which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired thereunto.</hi> Well, and ſo thought the <hi>Primate</hi> too. 'Tis a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that a Doctor of <hi>Divinity</hi> ſhould ſo unvvorthily handle a Reverend
<pb facs="tcp:33604:30"/> perſon, and faſten upon him a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in a matter vvherein he doth ſo perfectly agree with her. But he hath received the due deſert of his bitterneſſe, his Book being, as I am informed, burned by the hand of the common Hangman. And now Reader, thou wilt apply to me the ſpeech of <hi>Diogenes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Mindas,</hi> but I ſhall eaſe thy patience, when I have onely deſired thee to reſolve this moſt plaine and eaſie queſtion: <hi>Whether thoſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are contrary to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Compoſers of our Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which have been frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted by the divulgers of them, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by our Learned Profeſſors, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our civil authority, the contrary whereunto have been conſtantly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our Acts, the greateſt Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſolemnities, be the Doctrine of our Church of</hi> England.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:31"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pref. r. <hi>that I.</hi> r. <hi>none know.</hi> for <hi>one</hi> r. <hi>once.</hi> p. <hi>14.</hi> l. penult. r. <hi>Mat. 7.3, 4, 5.</hi> p. <hi>74.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> r. à Deo. p. <hi>77.</hi> l. <hi>24.</hi> r. <hi>'tis</hi> p. <hi>96.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> for <hi>them</hi> r. <hi>his reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſtakes in ſpelling, or in accenting Greek words, or in not diſtinguiſhing the members of ſentences, if I ſhould note, I ſhould too much diſtruſt the judgement of the Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33604:31"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, OR, A Juſtification of the Fathers and Schoolmen in their Opinion, <hi>That Sin hath not a Poſitive Beeing.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xerciſing my Miniſtry at <hi>Brackley,</hi> I came into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Barlee,</hi> who upon the publication of his <hi>Correptory Correction,</hi> was pleaſed to beſtow one Copy on me, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me freely to ſpend my thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: In my Anſwer, though I could not but Intimate how much I diſliked the ſharpnes of his ſtile, in ſome paſſages rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his adverſary, yet I could not but ſay, that there was ſomething in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative part, unto which <hi>Mr. Pierce</hi> would ſcarce be able to returne a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33604:32"/> Anſwer: Which my opinion I yet ſee no reaſon to recant. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his buſtle and ratlings, yet impartiall and judicious men may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne, he is but like that Goth in <hi>Proco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> who, though he fought fiercely, had the mortall arrows ſticking in his helmet, whereof he ſoon after fell. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had ſome part of his education a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Oxford Cavaliers, who were wont to outface their defeats with bone-fires, and to ring their Bells after the greateſt routs, and being a little tainted with that humour, reſolves to Triumph who ever gets the victory. And indeed a Spirit of moſt childiſh inſultation ſeems to have poſſeſſed as many, as have lift up an Engliſh pen againſt the <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox,</hi> in this quinquarticular controverſy. Il'e inſtance onely in Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> who in the Preface to his Triumviri, ſaith, <hi>that he hath not met with any thing in the writings of any, or of all the three men conteſting with him, which had in the leaſt ſhaken his confidence concerning the truth of the things by him aſſerted, or that, for the leaſt ſpace of time, put him to any ſtand or loſſe in his underſtanding concerning them, or to ſeek what to Anſwer to any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33604:32"/> thing they offer or object againſt any of them?</hi> which lines the greateſt charity muſt needs look upon as ſo much vapouring Rhetorick dropt from his pen, in the abſence of Judgment and conſcience: Or as an eſſay of the <hi>Spartanes</hi> valour, who being ſtruck down by a mortall blow, uſed to ſtop their mouths with earth, that they might not be heard to quetch or groan, thereby to affright their fellowes, or animate their Enemies. The reader hath not yet the occaſion of my calamity: Mr. <hi>Barlee</hi> reſolves to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Divine <hi>Philanthropie,</hi> and writes a ſecond letter to me, deſiring to borrow ſome books, and withall to know what I thought of his aſſailants reply: I had not then peruſed it, nor have I yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed it, nor ſhall I ever peruſe it, except I can find ſome of the Rabbines hours, which belong neither to night nor day. But it ſeems I had eſpyed that his ſtrange and long ſince exploded opinion of the poſitivity of ſin, which made me write, <hi>that if he held ſin to be poſitive, he muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold it to be from God,</hi> (which is the blaſphemy he chargeth upon the Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts) <hi>or elſe hold it to be God,</hi> which would be to beſtow an <hi>Apotheoſis</hi> on ſin. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33604:33"/> whatever poſitive thing is not from God, is God.</hi> This my friend, without any leave obtained or asked from me, puts in print under my name: with no ill intent, I hope, but yet ſome what againſt the rule of friendſhip. But having entituled me to the old, innocent, Metaphyſicall maxime, that <hi>omne ens eſt vel primum vel a primo,</hi> how doth Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> paratragaediate? How doth he tumble in his ugly Tropes, &amp; rowl himſelfe in his rayling eloquence? You would think he were ſome <hi>Tertullus,</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an angry Pariſhioner, to accuſe me before the Committee for ejection, of Ignorance, and ſcandall. I cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perfect affront to my Conſcience, and the rules of Chriſtianity, returne him blaſphemer for blaſphemer: For though I think the forementioned blaſphemy doth naturally and lineally deſcend from that opinion, which he firſt vented in his Philanthropy, and now ſeeks to maintain; yet I think it no way conſiſtent, with the ingenuity of a Scholar, or of a man, to charge an adverſary with that blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, which he every where diſclaimes, becauſe in my opinion ſuch a blaſphemy flowes from his principles. I know that the Lutherans are no better than infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33604:33"/> if they deny the reſurrection and aſcenſion of Chriſt, and am pretty confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that their opinion concerning the ubiquity of the humane nature, cannot conſiſt either with the one or with the other: ſhall I therefore ſay in print, that the Brethren of that perſwaſion deny thoſe two fundamentall Articles? nay rather let my right hand forget its skill, than write any thing of that nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. And yet this is the caſe of the Calviniſts, they hold an abſolute decree of reprobation, hence it followes, ſayes Mr. <hi>Pierce,</hi> that <hi>God is the Author of ſin,</hi> and <hi>that mans deſtruction is not of himſelf.</hi> They deny any ſuch conſequences can be inferr'd, and write books upon books, to ſhew the grounds and reaſons of their denyall, ſufficient one would think to ſtop the mouths of any calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, though as wide as a ſepulchre. Withall declaring that they refuſe not to be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the bittereſt <hi>Anathema's,</hi> if they ſhall be found to father the leaſt obliquity upon the moſt holy Law-giver. And yet Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> finds a forehead to ſay they make God the Author of Sin. And is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with thoſe that will not be as hugely uncharitable as himſelf. This he will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33604:34"/> pretend to do in great affection <hi>to the moſt vulgar and leſſe intelligent readers, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance &amp; liberty from the worſt kind of thraldome he doth eſpecially aime at in what he publiſheth;</hi> as he tels us Pag. 5. That the vulgar may not be in danger to ſtumble at what was written in Latine, by men ſome of whoſe names they ſcarce ever heard of, whoſe Books they to be ſure would never have bought, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath in great affection to their ſouls, tranſlated ſome of the worſt ſayings of tranſmarine Divines into Engliſh. You are indeed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do good to all, but eſpecially to thoſe vulgar ones of your own perſwaſion, and party, who are ſo exceedingly prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> and others, from whom you pretend to derive your frightfull expreſſions, that theyl' not be in any danger of being miſled by them. Therefore it would have been your wiſeſt courſe to have drawn a Catalogue out of the writings of Biſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> Dr. <hi>John</hi> &amp; Dr. <hi>Francis White,</hi> Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featley,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Prideaux,</hi> who were their friends in point of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, whoſe Books are moſt of them in Engliſh, and commonly to be had, and the Authors of them acknowledged to be men
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33604:34"/> of great deſert and piety, and ſo may be the more apt to do miſchief by inſtilling theſe killing Doctrines into the minds of men. But what if the maintainers of the abſolute decree did deſerve ſo ſevere a condemnation, how come I to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it? why, <hi>becauſe he cannot conceive how that argument of mine (If ſin is a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive entity, either God is the Author of it, or it is God,) ſhould flow from any other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine than my conceit of Gods predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (before his preſcience) of all events without exception.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd yet he knows that Ieſuits twenty &amp; ten do uſe this Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, who yet are the ableſt, acuteſt, and moſt malicious oppoſers of the abſolute decree, as ſtated by <hi>Calvin</hi> &amp; others of our reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed writers. I have already ſecured him that I ſtudy no retaliation, onely I will make bold to deal with him as <hi>Alexander</hi> did with his <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> take him a little by the bridle, and turne him to the Sun, that other men may ſee how he layes about him, though himſelf will not.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he joynes me with that <hi>commune dei hominumque odium, Mr. Hobbs,</hi> &amp; when he hath called me <hi>Hobbiſt,</hi> what can he ſay more, except he ſhould call me Devill? But did I give him any reaſon to joyn
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33604:35"/> me with that prodigious writer, or doth not Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> rather do this on the ſame account as <hi>Ithacius,</hi> who having no other virtue but his hatred to the Priſcillianiſts, became ſo wiſe in the end, that he ſet down all that differed from him for Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillianiſts? <hi>Sulpit. Sev. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 413. Both Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> ſay, that if God be the Author of the Action, then he is alſo the Author of the obliquity of the Action, and that there is no difference betwixt the ſinfull act, and the ſin of the act, and this he knowes I deny. And would the Reader think that I am an <hi>Hobbiſt</hi> for diſſenting from <hi>Hobbes,</hi> and Mr. <hi>P.</hi> an Anti-<hi>Hobbiſt</hi> for agreeing with him? That Authour is known to be one who exceedingly ſcornes the parts of all that differ from him, who contradicts the old received Philoſophy, who bitterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighs againſt Presbyterians. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Characters doe better fit me or my adverſary let others judge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in his title-page he makes me an example of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by which if he could be ſuppoſed to meane, that I were one that upon conſideration of my many unworthyneſſes condemne my ſelf, I muſt thank him for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33604:35"/> and pray unro Chriſt for grace that I may abound in ſo noble an effect and part of repentance; but queſtionleſſe with him I am <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſenſe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. i. e. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Theophylast,</hi> and this is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to call to all people to break of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar converſe with me, and to make me worſe then an Heretick; for he was not thought ſelf condemned till after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, and that by a Biſhop, ſaith Dr. <hi>Hammond;</hi> but he for a ſuppoſed overſight in Metaphyſicks thinks meet to print me ſuch to all the World, though I be to this day Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant whether there be a Biſhop <hi>in rerum naturâ,</hi> of a different opinion from me. <hi>Pref.</hi> that he might ſlurre mee he defiles his own conſcience all over with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; <hi>(thou wilt find men obtruding new Creeds on the Church, one inſerting this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, that God is no Spirit, another this, that God is the maker of all things reall, and ſo by conſequence unavoideable of all the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe in the World.)</hi> I confeſſe I had ſo much charity as to think hee intended not mee, but ſome other in this ſo high charge. But that I find him <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 163. thus deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf. Mr. <hi>Hick: builds backward,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33604:36"/> thus <hi>he layes it down as his principle, that God is the maker of all things that are reall without exception, therefore of</hi> Davids <hi>lying with</hi> Bathſhebah, <hi>therefore of his adultery.</hi> If in that ſentence which Mr. <hi>Barlee</hi> hath excerped out of my letter, he can find the word reall, then I muſt neceſſarily either explain, or condemne my ſelf; but having never uſed it, nor any terme ſynonymous, I might leave him with thoſe words deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered will thunder &amp; lightning, <hi>thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſſe.</hi> I ſay indeed that all things poſitive are either God, or from God: But is poſitive and reall all one? The darkneſſe (which he ſaith improperly enough, was created by God) no wiſe man will call poſitive, yet all will ſay that it was reall: privations are indeed ranked among <hi>entia rationis,</hi> but that is not becauſe they do not <hi>antecedere operationem intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus;</hi> for the aire would be darke, and <hi>Barti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus</hi> blind, though no one thought ſo; but they then become <hi>entia rationis</hi> when they are conceived of otherwiſe than they be, as when darkneſſe is conceived of as if it were ſome poſitive blackneſſe. But what if I had ſaid that God is the Author of all things reall, why muſt this be called an article of my faith, or an obtruding a new
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33604:36"/> article on the Church? Doth every one that gives his opinion, and brings an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to confirme it, make a new Creed? Then ſhall wee have more Creeds than there be ſound believers. Theſe are the two articles of my Creed, God is Holy, God is omnipotent, if any one do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialy aſſent to theſe, I ſhall give him the right hand of fellowſhip, if in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theſe two divine attributes he differ from mee, I ſhall not make him a blaſphemer, or expunge him out of the Catalogue of Chriſtians, but charitably ſuppoſe that his error, if not too groſſe, proceeds rather from want of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy than from want of piety, and do here once for all profeſſe before the ſearcher of hearts, who hates nothing more than Hypocriſy, and that ſevere Regiſter within me, to which I owe more reverence than to affront it with a will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lie, that I ſhould be the leſſe zealous in defending the privative nature of ſin, if I did not think that this my aſſertion were the moſt probable way of reconciling thoſe two Divine perfections of purity and omnipotence. I love Philoſophy onely as an handmaid to Divinity: as to thoſe Scholaſticall ſpeculations in which Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33604:37"/> is not at all concerned, I matter not much what opinion men be of, nor whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of any opinion at all. But I will not uſe ſo great ſeverity, as to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate his ſo unworthy ſpeeches, take them barely as thou findeſt them: <hi>Pref. I have envenomed Mr.</hi> Barlee, <hi>and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medled in his affairs, to ſuch a deſperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that if I preach as is printed, my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of all others have need of a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative:</hi> Pag. 11. <hi>I am one of the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious pair of writers:</hi> Pag. 107. cap. 3. <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>ſafeſt way is to ſpit in my face, who betrayed him to that ſenſeleſſe blaſphemous inference;</hi> Pag. 154. <hi>My argument is the moſt horrible of all, hard to ſay whether more impious or more unſcholarlike.</hi> Pag. 156. <hi>I muſt make ſome kind of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ſo ſcandalous an attempt.</hi> Ib. <hi>my medium is a crying and a killing Doctrine. I am a malefactor, and fallen headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dangers, nay reall miſchiefs, by my own wilfull precipitation of my ſelf and others.</hi> Pag. 157. <hi>He corrects himſelf for talking Metaphyſicks to ſuch a Scholar as I, who ſeeme ſo great a ſtranger to them, that he may very well take up the Proverbiall verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33604:37"/>
            <p>pag. 159. <hi>The brethrens way of arguing, is the fantaſtick creature of the brethren.</hi> Pag. 161. <hi>I am a Beetle flying in the face of the Eagle, ſtriking at God and his purity, by giving ſin an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and laying my child, when I have ſo done, at another mans door.</hi> Pag. 162. <hi>My traiterous child hath done exactly to me, as I thought to have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my brother.</hi> Pag. 164. <hi>I argue like the Libertines, and as it were out of their mouthes,</hi> Pag. 167. <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>is debauched by me.</hi> Pag. 175. <hi>My apprehenſion is ſadder than if I had thought Apotheôſis to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> pono. Ib. <hi>All I have diſcovered is my being overflown with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which could its banks have contained it, would not thus have guſhed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver upon no occaſion, when 'tis plain the effect could be no other, but to drown my credit with a yellow, as well as my cauſe with a blacker Jaundiſe.</hi> And for a concluſion I am bid to <hi>read, conſider,</hi> and <hi>apply</hi> what is ſpoken in <hi>Mark</hi> 3.28, 29, 30. as if I had done ſomething bordering upon the coaſts of the moſt accurſed blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt. Having with the Badger bitten till his teeth meet, he lets goe; and I trow it was high time: for was there ever a man, <hi>ab orbe condito,</hi> in whom malice,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33604:38"/> upon ſo ſmall, ſo no reaſon, raged at that tedious and importune rate and height? Hath this learned Rector been lately made free of the Cart? Doth he think he may raile by authority? Or was he ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to publiſh a Treatiſe dirty enough to transform the <hi>gilded Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a black one, able to juſtifie all the ugly brats of the wildeſt Sectaries that <hi>G. C.</hi> hath midwiv'd into the world? I utter not the words of paſſion, but ſobriety, knowing that many a poor ſcold hath been duckt in the Gumble-ſtool, many a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Quaker caſt into priſon, for words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably more civil and tollerable than moſt of thoſe beſtowed on me. Had my Antagoniſt been a reſident in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Mr. Vicecan. had been bound upon my complaint to have puniſht him with banition, or at leaſt with incarceration, or publick recantation; and yet Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who metes out all this hard meaſure to me, does every where complain of Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s foul language againſt himſelf; not regarding that of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> which I have thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Margin, nor that of the Apo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>le, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2, 3. nor that of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.34, 35. Nay, as if all this were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, he makes himſelf alſo guilty of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33604:38"/> greateſt Hypocriſie, by giving it out to the world, <hi>that he hath done no more than hee was in conſcience and duty bound to.</hi> p. 156. and <hi>Pref.</hi> he would needs perſwade me, <hi>That all he hath done is in order to my eaſe and ſafety too; and that I ought to be thank full for the diligent and impartial hand, which for ſome ſhort time doth ſeem to hurt me.</hi> But ſeeing he himſelf had the ſame <hi>Phagedaenous</hi> and eating ſores which he tels us were cured by good company, and good bookes, what neceſſity was there that mine ſhould be touch'd with either the launce or cauſtick? If he had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in ſuch a compoſition, whoſe every line is gall and wormwood, why did he not before he thus blur'd me with his blackeſt ink, Firſt, enquire whether ever I did write any ſuch thing to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> or no? For if Mr. <hi>B.</hi> be ſuch a lyar, as he repreſents him, why would he beleeve me the Author of ſo monſtrous an Argument, upon the bare Authority of his report? 2. How did he know whether I related this Argument as from my ſelf, and not onely as the Argument of others? Or 3. why did he not by ſome private letter, endeavour to purge the peccant humour, before he made the paſſionate adventure of calling
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33604:39"/> it <hi>obſtinate?</hi> Let's try whether wee can gheſs what might move Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who ſaies in his Letter to Doctor <hi>Bernard,</hi> that in all his dealing with Mr. <hi>B.</hi> he was not ſo much as heated, ſo to flame againſt me. Firſt; it was not ſure the Argument it ſelf; for that being uſed by Fathers, by School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of all Sects, by Proteſtant Writers of all perſwaſions, particularly by the moſt judicious Mr. <hi>Tho. Barlow</hi> (with whom for Metaphyſical Learning Mr. <hi>P.</hi> will in modeſty confeſs himſelf not worthy to be named in the ſame day) could not deſerve ſo ſevere a cenſure. Seeing he tells us, that he reſolves to doe nothing untill the <hi>moſt ſober, unbiaſſed perſons ſhall think it publickly uſefull,</hi> I ſhall make this requeſt to him, that hee would procure any one ſober perſon, to give it under his hand, that it was publickly uſefull to call all thoſe fooliſh and impious, who have uſed this Argument; or if ſuch Epithetes belong not unto others, why to me? O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have <hi>de induſtriâ</hi> printed the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereas I never thought that any thing which I wrote ſhould have come to the Preſs: nay what I did write, was written in ſuch haſte, that I might well ſay with <hi>Jerome, Qui non ignoſcit ingenio,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33604:39"/> ignoſcat tempori:</hi> But I believe the ſober men of his own perſwaſion, will be ſo far from approving his language, that they will rather let him taſte of <hi>Memnons</hi> diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, who hearing a mercenary Souldier, with many bold and impure reports, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt King <hi>Alexander,</hi> lent him a blow with his Launce, ſaying, That he had hired him to fight againſt <hi>Alexander,</hi> and not to raile.</p>
            <p>Secondly; though not the Argument in ſelf, yet my party and my Maſters, with whom he doth ſo frequently upbraid me, might juſtly move his choler: Indeed I find, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> guiltie of partiality to ſo deſperate a degree, that he makes Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm enough to a mans commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Anti-arminianiſm a blaſting of all graces, and an alloy to all endowments; as if it might be ſaid of his Opinion, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes of Diſcretion, <hi>Tolle hanc, &amp; virtus vitium erit.</hi> Once I finde him acknowledging, that Piety and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning might be found among the Abſolute Predeſtinarians, but being now faln from his firſt love, he thinks meet to brand Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> with the ſuſpicion of being an Hypocrite; as if becauſe he were a man of great parts and worth, he could not be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33604:40"/> in earneſt of that party whom he hath owned in Praying, in Preaching, in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting: Nay thoſe againſt whom he writes are <hi>the wicked,</hi> and ſo by him not onely thought, but alſo called in the <hi>Adv.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Bax:</hi> But as for thoſe that are for the reſpective Decrees, and are no friends to Presbytery, they are, <hi>eo nomine,</hi> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, excellent, renowned, immortal, what not? I will inſtance in two or three, upon whom he beſtows the greateſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſure not without ſome regret and recalcitration of his conſcience. Firſt, he bleſſeth the Author of an unlicenſed Pamphlet, called, <hi>An Hiſtorical relation of the Judgement of ſome moſt worthy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, holy Martyrs, and others, concerning Gods election. Divi. Phil. p.</hi> 93. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. with the honourable appellation of <hi>a moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divine and Confeſſour,</hi> and ſeems to bewaile it, that the book is in ſo few mens hands; but I ſhall let the Reader ſee, that if this book had had its deſert, it muſt have been in fewer mens hands than it is. The forementioned ſcurrilous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet was reprinted <hi>Anno</hi> 1631, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by Mr. <hi>Martin,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Laud's</hi> Chaplain: when Sir <hi>Humphrey Lind,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> complained to Archbiſhop
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33604:40"/> 
               <hi>Abbot</hi> of this execrable Impoſture, the book was called in, Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to his Grace, that he had given to his Chaplain ſuch a ratling, as would make him never meddle with Arminian books or opinions more; nay at the Lords Barr he ſaid, that he did put him out of his Chaplains place for licenſing that Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet. The firſt Author of this book was anſwered by Mr. <hi>Robert Crowly,</hi> as may be ſeen in our Univerſity Library, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>O</hi> 5. This <hi>Crowly</hi> was a fugitive for Religion in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, an eminent laborious Preacher in the time of Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> He not knowing the name of Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Confeſſour, calls him <hi>Cerberus;</hi> but Mr. <hi>John Veron</hi> the Queens Chaplain, who was principally concern'd in the book, found out his name to be <hi>Champneys,</hi> and in a Tract of his dedicated to her Majeſty, and called a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Doctrine of Predeſtination, ſpeaks thus of him <hi>[In this I comfort my ſelf, that his tongue is known to be no ſlander: For the like did he moſt proudly attempt, in your moſt gracious Brother good King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſixth's dayes, againſt all the godly Preachers of that time, calling them marked Miniſters of Antichriſt, and men void of the Spirit of God (for none, be they never ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33604:41"/> godly, never ſo earneſt and faithfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the Lords vineyard, have the Spirit of God, or doe know the efficacie of it but he onely) as many godly perſons be able to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie to his face: That he did therefore, and for many other abominable errours, which he then ſtoutly maintained, bear at that time a Faggot at</hi> Paul's-croſs, <hi>Father</hi> Coverdale <hi>making then the Sermon there. Belike fearing now the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that he ſhould be compell'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke his Pelagian-like opinion, he durſt not, for all his proud boaſt, ſet his own name to his railing and venemous bookes, nor yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to be ſold openly or publickly in the Book-ſellers ſhops, but cowardouſly ſuppreſſing both his own name, and the name of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and fooliſh Printer, got the whole Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion into his own hands, that ſo he might in huggermugger ſend them unto his private freinds abroad, whom belike he ſuſpected to be of his affinity and damnable opinion: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit this could not be wrought ſo privily, but that within a while, ſome of his bookes came into my hands, whereby ſhortly after the Printer was known, and brought to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, whom this ſtout champion of</hi> Pelagius <hi>hath left in the bryars; and leſt himſelfe ſhould be fain to ſhew a reaſon of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33604:41"/> doth keep himſelf out of the way ſtill, and dares not once ſhew his face: If he be able to maintain his Doctrine againſt my Book, let him come forth and play the man, I am ready at all times to yeeld to the truth, and unto the ſincere teachers thereof]</hi> And doth this Gentleman deſerve to be ſaluted a Confeſſor?</p>
            <p>A ſecond <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> whom he ſeekes to make white, is the Engliſh <hi>Tilenus;</hi> he's ſtiled the <hi>excellent,</hi> and this is ſaid of him; <hi>If he be alive to undertake his own cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>the world will find 'twill be but</hi> impar congreſſus: Yea he ſeems to complain, that <hi>he hath not the happineſs to know him in the leaſt degree.</hi> But what is there in this ſcribler that may deſerve ſuch Elogies? Firſt, he caſts the higheſt ſcorn upon the Tryers, making them to ask ſuch queſtions of thoſe that come before them, as in all probabilitie it never came into their thoughts to ask, which is ſuch a piece of Impudence, as no one hath ventured to imitate him in, but that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> of <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-ſtreet,</hi> whoſe hand being againſt all men, hath provoked all men, even the common Pamphleter to lift up a hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf. Secondly; This poor fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low makes himſelf an adverſary, out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33604:42"/> his own fancy, and driving him before him from one end of the Book to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhootes all his arrows at this man of ugly clouts of his own framing, as if it were that venerable Synod of <hi>Dort:</hi> And does he not deſerve to be call'd <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent?</hi> and to bee preferred to Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as to my party and Maſters, I have ſome ſatisfactory things to return in way of Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt; I have the thouſand witneſſes to atteſtate, that the deſires of my ſoul are, to receive a Diſciple in the name of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple, a Prophet in the name of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, not as concurring with me in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, concerning the Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min of Church Diſcipline. My cordiall affections to thoſe Epiſcopal Divines, whoſe endeavours are to promote that in which all confeſs the power of Godlyneſs to conſiſt, are as well known, as I my ſelfe am. And I challenge all the world to produce that eare that ever heard me ſpeak the leaſt ſyllable that might tend to inodiate the perſon, or to vilifie the parts and pains of any one Prelatiſt, becauſe ſuch.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33604:42"/>2. Though that little I have read of Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> Inſtitutions which, is not above the fourth part, makes me fully of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his mind, who ſaid <hi>in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtola Verini,</hi> he had rather be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Book, then of all that ever were made by <hi>Grotius;</hi> yet ſo unhappy is Mr. <hi>P.</hi> in gheſſing at my Maſters and the Books in which I converſe, that I can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fely profeſſe, as a preciſe and meaſured truth, when I ſent that letter to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> I had read more in Doctor <hi>Tailor,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> then I had in all thoſe Authors mentioned in his Title-page, upon whom he pretends to make <hi>occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reflections:</hi> And if Presbytery be a crime, I muſt needs ſay that I have learn't it from <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is this Presbytery to ſay that a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter and a Biſhop differ in degree one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not in order? that I learne from the late right Reverend the Primate of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, from Doctor <hi>Holland Regius</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, who ſo determined <hi>in Publicis Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis,</hi> in direct contradiction to Dr. <hi>Laud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Is this Presbytery to hold that an ordination by Presbyters is valid? That I learne from Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Scotchman Biſhop, never made
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33604:43"/> Prieſt but by Presbyters, which he would not have done, had ordination by Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſeemed unto him a nullity. I learn it from Biſhop <hi>Downam</hi> in his conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Sermon, <hi>Pag.</hi> 43. Who ſaith that the contrary opinion is proper to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: from Doctor <hi>Forbs,</hi> who in his <hi>Ireni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> largly proves it. Indeed among the Epiſcopall Divines I ſcarce know any contrary unto me in this, except thoſe who drew the ſcheme of their opinions after that Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was Lord of the houſe. And I think it no uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſay, that ſome of later times, in making their Judgements, had very great reſpect unto the Stars that were culmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is this Presbytery to aſſert the ſole power of Juriſdiction was not in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp; that they had no warrant to dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate their power unto a Lay Chancellour? This I learn from the judicious Lord <hi>Veru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,</hi> who ſaith, <q>that the firſt was a thing almoſt without example in good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore not unlikely to have crept in, in the degenerate and corrupt times. As to the 2. the deputation of their authority. I ſee no perfect and ſure ground for that neither; being ſomewhat
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33604:43"/> different from the examples &amp; rules of Government: we ſee in all Laws in the World offices of confidence and skill, cannot be put over, nor exerciſed by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties.</q> In his works printed 1657. <hi>p.</hi> 239. 240.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is this Presbytery to aver that after a great abuſe of the Epiſcopall power, the civil Magiſtrate might take it away root and branch, and commit the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church unto Presbyters, at leaſt for a ſeaſon? This I learn from the learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> at whoſe name Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is wont to riſe up in an extaſie of Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>de Imperio Sum. poteſt. chap.</hi> 11. Nay, if this be Presbytery to maintain the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter antiquity and primitiveneſſe of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery then <hi>Eſpiſcopacy,</hi> for that I need not conſult <hi>David Blondell,</hi> the Lord <hi>George Digby</hi> a great ſtickler for our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh prelacy ſo inform's mee in his letter to Sr. <hi>K. D.</hi> Pag. 119. <hi>The Presbytery of Scotland in point of Government hath a greater reſemblance then either yours or ours to the firſt age of Chriſts Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Is this Presbytery and <hi>Calviniſme</hi> to aſſert an abſolute decree of election and reprobation, and to manifeſt the greateſt indignation againſt thoſe who giue it out
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33604:44"/> unto the World, that thoſe opinions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take away the liberty of the will, or make God the Author of ſinne, this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I learn from <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> divines of the firſt magnitude. Reader, peruſe their words, and then tell me whether I miſtake their meaning. Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> calls <hi>Biſhop</hi> for aſperſing the forementioned tenent, as if it made God the Author of ſin, <hi>Elymas,</hi> and his fellow <hi>Wright</hi> on the ſame ſcore, <hi>foul mouth'd dogge, and a filthy ſwine, who wallowing in the muck &amp; dirt of Popiſh Ignorance, hath his eyes ſo daubed up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that he ſeeth not his own way.</hi> Anſwer to the Preface. All this in a book dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to King <hi>James,</hi> who in requital of his paines beſtowed on him the Biſhoprick of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Yea the forementioned Writer in his Defence againſt Mr. <hi>Higgons</hi> ſaith, <hi>That if</hi> Luther <hi>have any where in that lewd and impious manner calumniated the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>he will not deny but that Mr.</hi> Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons <hi>ſhould have cauſe to ſtile him a foule mouth'd dog.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Apoſtate <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> objected this againſt the ſame Doctrine, what words Dr. <hi>Crakanthorpe</hi> thought meet to uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, Mr. <hi>Barlee</hi> hath already told Mr. <hi>Pierce:</hi> I ſhall onely adde the Book
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33604:44"/> was dedicated to King <hi>Charles,</hi> and hath this title put to it, <hi>Defenſio Eccleſiae Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae;</hi> of which Church Mr. <hi>P.</hi> profeſſeth himſelf a dutifull and obedient ſon; and that Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> ſaith of that Treatiſe, that it was <hi>the moſt accurate peece of controverſie that was written ſince the Reformation.</hi> Next let us hear the moſt learned and peaceable Dr. <hi>Sanderſon, con.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Clerum, p.</hi> 29, 30. <hi>Sundry of the Doctors of our Church teach truly and agreeably to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the effectual concurrence of Gods will and power, with ſubordinate agents in every, and therefore even in ſinfull actions; Gods free election of thoſe whom he purpoſeth to ſave of his own grace, without any motives in or from themſelves; the immutability of Gods love and grace towards the Saints E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and their certaine perſeverance therein to ſalvation; the juſtification of ſinners by the imputed righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, apprehended and applied unto them by a lively faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the works of the Law. Theſe are ſound and true, and (if rightly underſtood) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and right profitable doctrines; and yet they of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>have the forehead, (I will not ſay to ſlander, my Text alloweth more,) to blaſpheme God and his Truth, and the Miniſters thereof, for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33604:45"/> them;</hi> Bellarm. Gretſer, Maldonate, <hi>and the Jeſuites, but none more than our own Engliſh Fugitives,</hi> Briſtow, Stapleton, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Kelliſon, <hi>and all the rabble of that crew freely ſpend their mouthes in barking againſt us, as if we made God the author of ſinne; as if we would have men ſin and be damned by a fatal neceſſitie; ſinne whether they will or no; be damned whether they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it or no; as if we opened a gap to all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe and prophaneſſe; let them believe it is no matter how they live, heaven is their own cock ſure; as if we cried down Good Works, and condemned Charity: Slanders loud and falſe, yet eaſily blown away with one ſingle word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; theſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon us and our doctrine are unjuſt, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let them that miſreport us know, that without repentance their damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be juſt.</hi> Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> B. 3. p. 117. <hi>The next Hereſie which they ſay we are fallen into, is the Hereſie of</hi> Florinus, <hi>who taught that God is the author and cauſe of ſinne; This, ſaith</hi> Bellarm. Calvin, Luth. Martyr <hi>have defended in their writings; of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and wicked, and lying report, we are ſure God is not the author, but the devil.</hi> &amp; pag. 140. Cal. <hi>Then is not worſe than the</hi> Manichees, <hi>in making God the author of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33604:45"/> thoſe evils which the</hi> Manichees <hi>attribute to an evil beginning, as</hi> Bellarm. <hi>is pleaſed to pronounce of him; but is farther from that helliſh conceit than</hi> Bellarm. <hi>is from hell it ſelfe, if he repent not of theſe helliſh ſlanders.</hi> Dr. <hi>Ward.</hi> prae. de pecca. orig. p. 148. <hi>Prodiit non ita pridem clanculum liber, quem author intitulavit, amor dei erga genus humanum, qui acriter contendit ex conceſſis ſublap. ſatis evidenter inferri omnium pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum hominum reproborum deum eſſe verum &amp; principalem authorem. Audax aſſertum vel verius impudens calumnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might mention more, but I forbeare, and doe earneſtly deſire thoſe Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Divines, who cloſe with us in the points of preſent conteſt, that they would bethink themſelves and conſider, what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they muſt expect from theſe Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Ardelio's,</hi> no more than what <hi>Polyphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> promiſed <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> to be laſt devoured. If they cannot fall down and worſhip the Idols which theſe men have ſet up, they muſt expect to be thrown into the fierie furnace; nay they are tormented in it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſenſe, who calls <hi>the mouth of an angry adverſary</hi> by that name; for mark his word, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>Whatever diſhonours have been done unto the Proteſtant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33604:46"/> name by thoſe of the Kirk, or Conſiſtory, or their adherents here in England, yet the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſons of the Church of England have ever been free from any part of that guilt.</hi> This doth expunge Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Brownerig,</hi> whom we (as they deſerve) call Fathers, out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the dutifull Sonnes of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Nay he ſticketh not in the <hi>Preface to the Reader,</hi> p. 6. to place them among <hi>the very unſound and unruly members of this Church.</hi> Let me take the boldneſs to beſeech them who are of any authority in that party, as they love the truth, than which nothing ought to be more precious, as they tender the wellfare and ſafety of poor ſoules, for whom Chriſt dyed, that they would either plainly ſay, that they have all this while been miſtaken, and through ignorance Preached and Printed Blaſphemy, or elſe brand this falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer with the letter <hi>K,</hi> which when the I aw I allude to was made, was the firſt letter of the word <hi>Calumniator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I have ſpent more time in reading the Authors <hi>Pro</hi> &amp; <hi>Con</hi> about theſe points, than ever I intend to doe, being of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that the greateſt Scholars will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33604:46"/> be able fully to ſatisfie their own, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Reaſons about them: Nor ſhould this ſeem any wonder to us, who cannot be ignorant how many points there be in Natural Philoſophy, in which a man plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelf into inextricable difficulties, whether he affirm or deny them. With what confidence have I heard one young Sophiſter maintain, that <hi>continuum fit ex indiviſibilibus?</hi> and another, that <hi>continuum non fit ex indiviſibilibus?</hi> both thought themſelves in the right; but men of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture judgements ſtanding by, could eaſily ſee, that neither the one, nor the other could free his Aſſertion from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Objections brought againſt it. I thank God I have not the leaſt temptation to doubt concerning the Trinity of the Perſons, nor the Hypoſtatical Union of the two Natures; yet I never thought my ſelf able to vindicate thoſe myſteries from all the ſubtile Arguments and niceties of unbelieving ſophiſters. The like I think concerning the Doctrine of Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and the manner of the Spirits working Grace in the hearts of the Elect, theſe are matters ſo very myſterious, and my underſtanding ſo dark, that <hi>I</hi> can ſcarce hope ever in this world to be freed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33604:47"/> from all ſcruples about them. Would you therefore know why I hold Abſolute, Eternal, Perſonal Election, Efficacious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining Grace, and the certain infallible perſeverance of all Believers; Truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I finde theſe opinions moſt agreeable to Scripture, to the <hi>communis ſenſus fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium,</hi> the inſtinct and impulſe of the new creature in all ages; and, becauſe I finde they doe moſt tend to the debaſing of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, and to the exaltation of Chriſt my Saviour, and that free Grace of his, by which I hope to be acquitted at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>To this end I will relate two Hiſtoricall paſſages, with which J have been much taken; the one from Father <hi>Paul</hi> (who hath filled the Chriſtian world with his admiration) <hi>Hiſt: of the Counc. of Trent, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 212. he ſpeaking of the debates in that Aſſembly concerning theſe two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, thus expreſſeth himſelf. <hi>The firſt opinion</hi> (which is the opinion Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſo declaimes againſt) <hi>as it is hidden, and myſtical, keeping the minde humble, and relying on God, without any confidence in it ſelf, knowing the deformitie of ſinne, and the excellencie of divine grace, ſo the ſecond was plauſible and popular, cheriſhing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33604:47"/> humane preſumption, and making a great ſhew, it pleaſed more the preaching Fryars, then the underſtanding Divines, and the Courtiers thought it probable as conſonant to politick reaſons, it was maintained by the Biſhop of</hi> Bitonto, <hi>and the Biſhop of</hi> Salpi <hi>ſhewed himſelf very partiall, the defenders of this uſing humane reaſon prevailed againſt the others, but coming to the teſtimonies of the Scripture they were manifeſtly overcome.</hi> The other ſtory I find in the Preface to the <hi>Parallells,</hi> drawn up, as I ſuppoſe, by Doctor <hi>Featly,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Good. Acca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> Baron of <hi>Dona,</hi> reſiding ſome months in England, to ſolicite the recovery of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> was often ſet upon, and much laid at by a ſtranger there, named <hi>Roergheſt,</hi> a man deeply engaged in the Arminian party, who though he could not draw him from the truth to that ſide, yet caſt ſuch miſts of doubts before him, that his Lordſhip, for better clearing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the conference of ſome Engliſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines verſed in Controverſies of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and opportunely meeting with two at once, he demanded of them why the Divines of England ſo generally diſtaſted the Doctrine broached by Arminians, their anſwer was, that <hi>albeit thoſe tenents
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33604:48"/> were plauſible to corrupt reaſon, and ſet out to the beſt advantage by the wit and art of the Patrons thereof; yet that the ſacred Scriptures, to which naturall reaſon muſt bow and ſtricke ſail, throughly ſearched and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially ſcanned gave no ſupport at all to the new modell of Gods councells framed in mans braines; and that the prime Fathers of moſt eminent note in the Church, above twelve hundred years ago, at the firſt birth of thoſe miſhape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brats daſhed them againſt the ſtones, and conſequently that by the ſame</hi> Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>ancient Church the new Revivers of thoſe errors at this day were</hi> damnati antequàm nati, <hi>precondemned in the loines of their parents.</hi> The Baron ſomewhat affected with this anſwer, replied, <hi>certe ſi Arminius Pelagium refodit, merito vos Arminium defoditis.</hi> Not long after the ſaid ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor came to the Baron again, hoping to make him his Proſelite, the Baron ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him with the Engliſh Divines anſwer, he was at firſt ſo confident as to ſay, <hi>quid tandem Arminio cum Pelagio?</hi> But when thoſe Divines had exhibited to the Baron a <hi>Paralell</hi> betwixt them, ſince printed, this confident Gentleman, though he undertook to returne forthwith a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and punctuall anſwer, <hi>quitted the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33604:48"/> field, took Sea and returned into Holland, and was never heard of more.</hi> I know Mr. <hi>P. alſo</hi> doth very much fume to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Pelagian, Semi-pelagian, Maſſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> &amp;c. But if his feet were not crooked, how came their ſhoes to fit him ſo well? I remember a ſaying of Doctor <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in his fifth Sermon, <hi>ad Populumi, that the Propheſies of ſaint</hi> Paul <hi>and ſaint</hi> John <hi>make it ſo unqueſtionable that Rome is the ſeat of</hi> Antichriſt, <hi>that they who will needs be ſo unreaſonably charitable, as to think the Pope is not</hi> Antichriſt, <hi>may at leaſt wonder by what ſtrange chance it fell out that theſe Apoſtles ſhould draw the picture of</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt <hi>in every point and limbe ſo juſt like the Pope, and yet never think of him;</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> his quick wit hath prevented me in the application, never did the ſtile of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate writer belong to man, if not to him, ſuppoſing him to have no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with thoſe old Hereticks, for he hath formed no weapon, againſt which I cannot furniſh my ſelf with armour from the Magazine of Auſtin and others, who had to do with <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>But it may be the party with whom he ſuppoſeth me to ſay a confederacy are, the Puritans, for thoſe he cannot name with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33604:49"/> any patience or moderation he tells us (advertiſement to Mr. <hi>Baxter) that they were defined at</hi> Hampton Court, <hi>to be prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants frighted out of their wits, ſuch as are known to be painted ſepulchres, having the forme onely of godlineſſe, without the power of it: thought by judicious</hi> Hooker <hi>to be fit inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants for a wilderneſs, not for a well ordered City. Such as have ever deſpiſed dominion, and ſpoken ill of dignities, have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly boutefeus, and men of bloud, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbiall Authors &amp; Fautors of ſedition and violence in Church and ſtate.</hi> The words of the relator of the <hi>Hampton Court</hi> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence are theſe: <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. <hi>This and ſome other motions ſeeming to the King and Lords very idle and frivolous, occaſion was taken in ſome by-talke, to remember a certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription which Mr.</hi> Butler <hi>of Cambridge made of a Puritan, A Puritan is a proteſtant frayed out of his wits.</hi> And muſt what is ſaid in ſome by-talke be called <hi>defining?</hi> If I were minded to pay Maſter <hi>P.</hi> in his own coine, how eaſily might I tell him, that the Arminians were defined by a wiſe King in a premeditated declaration <hi>Atheiſticall ſectaries,</hi> that many of them are known to have neither the <hi>forme nor the power of godlineſſe,</hi> of whom judicious
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33604:49"/> 
               <hi>Amyraldus</hi> ſaith, that they can ſcarce be ſuppoſed <hi>ever to have felt the power of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> concerning whom the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid King ſaid <hi>that if they were not with ſpeed rooted out, no other iſſue could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected than the curſe of God, infamy through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the reformed Churches, and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall rent and diſtraction in the whole body of the State,</hi> concerning whom alſo the States themſelves ſaid, <hi>that they had created them more trouble than the King of Spain had by all his wars.</hi> And one would think the King and the States ſhould know better how to ſet the ſaddle upon the right Horſe then Maſter <hi>P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Theſe were Presbyterated Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, our Engliſh <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> Arminians are free from any ſuch guilt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Concerning them, not I, but the Viſcount <hi>Falkland</hi> ſhall ſpeak, who as he had more courage than to be afraid of them, ſo had he more ingenuity than to wrong them, in the before commended ſpeech to the houſe of Commons, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter</hi> Speaker, <hi>he is a great ſtranger in Iſrael who knows not that this Kingdome hath long laboured under many and great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, both in Religion and liberty, and his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33604:50"/> acquaintance here is not great, or his ingenuity leſſe, who doth not both know and acknowledge that a great, if not a principall, cauſe of both theſe, hath been ſome Biſhops and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents. Maſter</hi> Speaker, <hi>a little ſearch will ſerve to find them to have been the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of unity, under pretence of uniformity, to have brought in ſuperſtition and ſcandall under the titles of reverence and decency; to have defiled our Church, by adorning our Churches: to have ſlackned the ſtrictnes of that union which was formerly between us and thoſe of our Religion beyond the Sea, an action as unpolitick as ungodly.</hi> And becauſe I know the Reader will not account me tedious whileſt I uſe the words of ſo elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent a Lord, I ſhall recite more paſſages from him to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. <hi>We ſhall find of them to have both kindled &amp; blown the Common fire of both Nations, to have both ſent and maintained that book, of which the Author hath no doubt long ſince wiſhed with</hi> Nero, utinam nefciſſem lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, <hi>and of which more then one Kingdome hath cauſe to wiſh, that when he writ that, he had rather burned a Library, though of the value of</hi> Ptolomies. <hi>We ſhall find them to have been the firſt and principall cauſe of the breach, I will not ſay of, but ſince the paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33604:50"/> at</hi> Barwick, <hi>we ſhall finde them to have been the almoſt ſole abettors of my Lord of</hi> Strafford, <hi>whilſt he was practiſing upon another kingdom, that manner of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which he intended to ſettle in this, where he committed ſo many, ſo mighty, and ſo manifeſt enormities, as the like have not been committed by any Governour in any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſince</hi> Verres <hi>left</hi> Sicilie. <hi>And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had called him over from being De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of</hi> Ireland, <hi>to be in a manner Deputy of</hi> England <hi>(all things here being governed by a Juntillo, and that Juntillo governed by him) to have aſſiſted him in the giving of ſuch counſels, and the purſuing of ſuch courſes, as it is a hard and meaſuring caſt, whether they were more unwiſe, more unjuſt, or more unfortunate, and which had infallibly been our deſtruction, if by the grace of God their ſhare had not been as ſmall in the ſubtletie of Serpents, as in the innocence of Doves.</hi> But in entitling the honeſt Puritanes to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold violences that have been attempted or practiſed in Church and State, he borrows a piece of policy from the Jeſuits, who if they had proſpered in blowing up the Parliament houſe, had intended to give it about, that that ſo horrid and helliſh a fact was perpetrated by he knows whom. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33604:51"/> Biſhop <hi>Carleton</hi> in his Examination of Mr. <hi>Montagues</hi> Appeal, ſaith; <hi>That albeit the Puritans diſquieted the Church about their conceived Diſcipline, yet they never moved any quarrel about the Doctrine of our Church, and that till</hi> Montague <hi>there was no Puritan Doctrine known.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> ſaith in his anſwer to the Popiſh Atti: <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>Hee that makes difference between the Proteſtants and Puritans in matters of Faith, doth it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorantly or maliciouſly.</hi> Mr. <hi>T. Fuller</hi> 610. p. 99. <hi>We muſt not forget that</hi> Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>(I am confident I am not miſtaken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) was the firſt who profeſſing himſelf a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, uſed the word</hi> Puritan <hi>to ſignifie the defenders of matters doctrinal in the Engliſh Church. Formerly the word was onely taken to denote ſuch as diſſented from the Hierarchy in Diſcipline and Church-government, which now was extended to brand ſuch as were Anti-arminians in their judgement.</hi> So that by Puritanes, in all probability muſt be meant <hi>non-conformiſts.</hi> And if Mr. <hi>P.</hi> dare ſay, that ſuch men as Mr. <hi>Paul Baine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Hilderſham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cleaver</hi> the Decalogiſts; Mr. <hi>Tho. Hooker,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Ball,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Shepheard,</hi> were void of the power of godlyneſs, or that they had not more of it than had their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33604:51"/> he muſt either expect not to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or ſeek ſome other place than <hi>England</hi> to vent his paſſion in.</p>
            <p>If by the Puritanes he meaneth the gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Browniſts, I have not a word to ſay in their excuſe, but this, that the Prelaticall oppreſſion was ſuch, as might have made wiſer people than they madde. Had they not a colourable pretext to call ſome of our Prelates Antichriſtian, whoſe Courts vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſundry laborious Preachers, becauſe they could not bow at the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> when as ſundry idle ſots, whom they might frequently obſerve to ſtagger in the ſtreets, were never queſtioned.</p>
            <p>But the moſt probable ground of his fury is yet behind, my being noted by Mr. <hi>Barlee</hi> in the Margin, to be a man of his own Colledge: for doe but obſerve the phraſes and periods of the man upon this occaſion. <q>For ought I know he may be alſo in poſſeſſion of mine own Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and mine own Chamber, and mine own meat and drink, and thoſe yearly revenues which are mine own too; and for the which I may the rather expect to have ſome ſatisfaction, becauſe it ſeems the Viſitors made him one of my Receivers and Uſufructuaries (for my
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33604:52"/> legitimate heir or ſucceſſor they could not make him) And I have reaſon to be glad that he is thought ſuch a pious and learned man; becauſe if he is pious, he will the ſooner pay me my Arrears; and if he is learned, he will not object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my known and indiſputable right <hi>pag.</hi> 155. and <hi>Div. Phil. p.</hi> 147. I ſuffered the loſs of what I thought to be the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt poſſeſſion on earth; for being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly ſuggeſted to be the Author of ſome bookes, which to this very day I could never hear named; and though I earneſtly deſired that I might hear my ſelf accuſed, and know diſtinctly my accuſation, and be heard ſpeak for my ſelf, yet Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> could not obtaine that for me.</q> Thus he hath thrown his fierie darts at me, at farre the greater part of Heads and Fellows of Colledges in <hi>Oxon:</hi> at the Viſitors, and at the two Houſes of Parliament. But I know not how I am ſo little ſollicitous concerning the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe Darts, that I find my ſelf car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with a very pleaſing diverſion concerning two different kinds of ſober diſtraction or melancholy; the one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the brain is generally and equally ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to all objects; the other, where the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33604:52"/> diſtemper is confined to ſome one object or other; the brain being otherwiſe very ſound and ſober upon all other objects and occaſions. So <hi>Laurentius</hi> tells us of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, that otherwiſe had his ſenſes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perfect, and would diſcourſe of any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect very rationally, but was perſwaded that he was <hi>glaſs.</hi> And <hi>Huartus</hi> tels us of a Noble mans foot-boy in <hi>Italy,</hi> that thought himſelf a <hi>Monarch:</hi> And <hi>Joſephus Acoſtae</hi> tells us a ſadder ſtory of a Doctor of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, who would affirm, that <hi>he ſhould be a King and a Pope too; the Apoſtolical See being tranſlated to thoſe parts of</hi> America: which, together with ſome other frantick diſtempers, made him condemned to the fire for an Heretick. Farre be it from me to wiſh or preſage any ſuch kind of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> for his impudence againſt the ſupream Authority of the Nation; but I am under ſome temptation to think, that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> how diſcreet and ſober ſoever in other matters, is fallen into ſome Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condriacall conceits much of that nature; for what elſe could make him, after that he hath been known for ſome years, to be an Husband, and peaceably to have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Rectory of <hi>Brington,</hi> to talk of an indiſputable right to a Fellowſhip, cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33604:53"/> meat, and drink, yearly revenues in <hi>Magdalene</hi> Colledge? Nay, he prints as if he had right unto two Fellowſhips, one for Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and another for Mr. <hi>Pierce,</hi> how elſe am I but one of his Receivers? Let's try whether by a few queſtions we can make him more ſober,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What would hee have me pay him Arrears for? the <hi>uſus fructus</hi> is mine; why elſe am I ſaid to be made <hi>uſufructuary?</hi> An <hi>uſufructuary</hi> wanteth nothing but the title; he hath <hi>jus in re,</hi> though not <hi>ad rem.</hi> Well, ſith he doth ſo pleaſe himſelf in a title to yearly revenues at <hi>Magd.</hi> Coll. I ſhall deſire him to look over his Poſt-predicaments once more, and there hee ſhall finde, that the <hi>modus habendi uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> is by <hi>Logicians</hi> called <hi>peſſimus:</hi> by which they mean, that it is the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, but to a Fellow of a Colledge it is the worſt on another account, becauſe it doth evacuate and nullifie his title to all Academical enjoyments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Had he not better have ſaid nothing, than ſaid any thing, which might look like an affirmation, that he ſuffered the loſſe of his ſweeteſt enjoyment, for being ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Author of a Libel? When as we all know, that he was turned out, not by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33604:53"/> the Viſitors, but by the Comittee of Lords and Commons, for non ſubmiſſion to the Authority of Parliament in viſiting the Univerſity, for the doing of which a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was reſerved in the Articles granted by the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> at the ſurrender.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it not impudence to ſay, that the Viſitors authoriſed by the two Houſes, under the broad Seale of <hi>England,</hi> could not make me his legitimate ſucceſſour? Let him alſo ſay, that the Honourable Judges are Murderers, or elſe tell us how the Parliament, which could give them power to take away mens lives, could not alſo give power to others to take away his Fellowſhip. I have all this while gratified him in his ungrounded ſuppoſition, upon which his pen did run ryot, <hi>viz.</hi> my being in his Chamber, and ſucceeding him in his Fellowſhip, but the truth is (and that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had opportunity to know) his place was void before I was ſo much as Demy, nor am I in poſſeſſion of the Chamber which was once his. For a concluſion, I ſhall deſire this my Adverſary to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with his own heart, and impartially to enquire whether it be not envy, and not conſcience, which maketh him to exclaim with ſo much bitterneſs againſt the late
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33604:54"/> ejections, ſequeſtrations, deprivations; and whether he was ſo much offended at thoſe who enjoyed the places of ſuch Heads, or Fellows of Colledges as were ejected, whileſt <hi>Oxon</hi> being a Garriſon was not <hi>Oxon;</hi> and whether our late ſequeſtrations (which yet I undertake not in all things to acquit) were not more juſtifiable than thoſe proceedings in the late Archb. times, when men were ſuſpended <hi>ab officio &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio,</hi> meerly for not reading the <hi>Book of Sports.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having removed the rubbiſh, we may now come at the queſtion, which is, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moral evil, as ſuch, be a privation?</hi> Concerning which, the termes being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, 'twill be no difficult matter to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. What evill in general is, can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſcarce be declared by any one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon definition, nor hath ſuch a definition been attempted by any but <hi>Voetius</hi> the ſon, in his <hi>Theol. Nat: p.</hi> 539. ſometimes things very perfect and poſitive are called evil, as the venemous qualities in Plants, not that they are evill in themſelves, but by <hi>extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall denomination,</hi> in regard of their <hi>effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie,</hi> of this kind of evill we now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute not. And indeed nothing is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid to be evill, but that which is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33604:54"/> ſuch by <hi>intrinſecal denomination,</hi> as wanting ſome either <hi>natural,</hi> or <hi>moral perfection</hi> that it ought to have. The moſt common diviſion of evill is into evill of <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and evill of <hi>ſin,</hi> called by <hi>Tertullian, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſupplicii,</hi> and <hi>malum delicti:</hi> by <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Our debate is of the evill of ſin, which onely can be called morall evill. The next term is the reſtrictive particle <hi>(as)</hi> by which we underſtand <hi>malum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliter ſumptum,</hi> ſin conſidered <hi>abſtractly</hi> from that either <hi>act, habit,</hi> or <hi>faculty</hi> in which it is, and unto which it gives de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination. The not diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>ſinfull act,</hi> and the <hi>ſin of the act,</hi> is the ſtone at which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath all along ſtumbled. He tells me, <hi>that ſin being a</hi> complexum quid <hi>in the acknowledgement of all, cannot admit of an abſtraction, and yet remain the</hi> complexum <hi>that it was before abſtraction,</hi> p. 164. very wiſely and warily ſpoken; as who ſhould ſay, I cannot ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, but I muſt abſtract; I cannot indeed abſtract ſin from a ſinfull action, ſo as it ſhould ſtill remain ſinfull; nor can I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract whiteneſſe from a white wall ſo as that it ſhould ſtill remain white; for 'tis conſtituted white by whiteneſſe: But
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33604:55"/> though it be the whiteneſſe that makes it white, yet it is not the whiteneſſe that makes it a wall; and therefore I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the whiteneſſe and the wall apart: The Abſtract and Concrete word doe both ſignifie the ſame <hi>form,</hi> but not in the ſame way; becauſe the Concrete doth <hi>in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo</hi> connote that <hi>ſubject</hi> unto which the <hi>denominating forme</hi> agrees; but if at any time the Concrete be uſed with a <hi>redupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> then it is all one with the Abſtract, ſaith <hi>Smigleſius;</hi> indeed <hi>album qua album,</hi> and <hi>albedo</hi> differ little. Sinfull ſignifies both the <hi>ſubject</hi> that is <hi>ſinfull,</hi> and it's <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, ſin</hi> or <hi>ſinfulneſs,</hi> the <hi>meer pravity</hi> and <hi>irregularitie:</hi> Bus this will not down with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> therefore he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 83. 1. <hi>That action and quality are both acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</hi> 2. <hi>That an accident is not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of an accident.</hi> 3. <hi>That ſome acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are ſeparable from their ſubjects of inheſion, ſome not, as riſibility from a man.</hi> Bluſh all you that have any reſpect for <hi>Magd. Coll.</hi> to finde that one that was for ſome years Fellow of that Foundation, ſhould be ignorant of that which Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of two Terms ſtanding commonly know. May not an <hi>Accident</hi> be the <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſubject</hi> of <hi>inheſion to an accident,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33604:55"/> though onely <hi>ſubſtance</hi> can be the <hi>ultimate?</hi> If not, then the Queſtion, <hi>An fides ſit in Intellectu, an in voluntate,</hi> with ſix hundred more of the like nature, are at an end. Or what if the Action were but the Subject of Denomination, might not its evill bee diſtinct from it? Nor would this exact Gentleman, if he had to do with a Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, eſcape the laſh, for calling Riſibilitie an Inſeparable Accident, it being the moſt common inſtance of a Propriety, betwixt which, and an Inſeparable Accident, there is a moſt groſſe difference. But if hee think that the evill quality doth as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily flow from the Eſſence of an Action, as Riſibility doth from the Eſſence of a man (which he muſt think, unleſſe hee hath written ridiculous impertinencies) I conceive he hath not one man alive of his judgement. Yet at laſt, in a lucid inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, he tells us, p. 84. <hi>He can diſcern a difference betwixt the Action and its quality, by which it is evil.</hi> Let him but ſtick to that diſtinction, and I'le ne'r put him to diſtinguiſh between the ſame evil action and it ſelf: Nor did any one elſe; but he hath frequently frightfull apparitions in his own fancy, in the vanquiſhing whereof he takes not a little pride. Nor will I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33604:56"/> offend his terſe eares, with ſuch a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous word as <hi>pecceity,</hi> which he tels us oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs not in any Author ſacred or prophane. Onely I muſt obſerve how variouſly his pulſe beats, p. 13. <hi>Sin it ſelf is a Phyſicall Abstract at the groſſeſt, of which ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at least is an Abſtract Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, which admitting not any compoſition, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not further be Abſtracted, no not ſo much as in Imagination.</hi> p. 78. c. 2. <hi>Sin is a Concrete in reſpect of ſinfulneſs, and doth note the ſame thing in one word, thot ſinfull action doth in two, which I will make him to apprehend, do he what he can to the contrary: beſides, not reading what I write, by ſhewing that a ſinne and a ſinfull action, or act, or motion, have the ſame enunciation in all propoſitions imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable:</hi> p. 84. <hi>To prevent a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I give this notice to to Mr.</hi> W. <hi>that if the word</hi> wickedneſſe <hi>be not alwaies ſynonymous with ſinne, yet it is ſo often:</hi> pag. 164. <hi>Sin is a</hi> complexum quid <hi>in the acknowledgement of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſin is a <hi>complexum quid,</hi> is not acknowledged by all, or any; except by <hi>complexum</hi> you'll mean <hi>complexum ex ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere &amp; differentlâ;</hi> for ſin is an abſtract word, and doth not in it's ſignification connote any ſubject.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33604:56"/>2. It hath neither truth nor ſenſe in it, that a ſin, and a ſinfull act, or action, or motion, have the ſame enunciation in all Propoſitions Imaginable; I can ſay, not to doe what a man is bound to doe is a ſin; but I hope it is not a ſinfull act, or action, or motion; ſin may be predicated of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal and habitual corruption, ſo cannot ſinfull act, or action. Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> explain how ſin is a Phyſical abſtract, and how it is ſynonymous to the word <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> and yet ſignifieth but the ſame thing in one word, that ſinfull action doth in two, and he ſhall reconcile what to me ſeemes not reconcileable. If I had ſaid <hi>albedo</hi> is a concrete in reſpect of <hi>albedineitas,</hi> and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified that in one word, which <hi>ſuperficies alba</hi> doth in two, I ſhould be thought at <hi>Magd.</hi> Coll. to forget my ſelf extreamly. And to prevent a Logomachy, I further adde, that ſin and ſinfulneſs are to me ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymous, and therefore perhaps I may uſe them promiſcuouſly, meaning by them what the Latines doe by <hi>peccatum, pravitas, malitia,</hi> and the Greeks by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Little probability may the Reader think wee ſhould agree; for hee ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 150, 151. <hi>That ſinis ſo perfectly a Concrete, that unleſſe it is a Concrete, it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33604:57"/> cannot be conceived to be a ſin, no more than a concrete can be conceived not to be a concrete;</hi> but I ſay that ſin is ſo perfectly an abſtract, that if we conceive not of it as an abſtract, we conceive not of it as ſin; I am to ſeek what <hi>vox Abſtracta</hi> is, if ſin be not ſuch.</p>
            <p>The third term is privation: which I muſt the rather explain, becauſe he tells me, <hi>Pag.</hi> 162. <hi>That I ſeem to make no difference between a ſimple Negative, and a Privative.</hi> A Privation with me, (as with all others) is the abſence of a poſitive form, in a ſubject capable of ſuch a form: Inſtances are commonly given of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, deafneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>P. indeed,</hi> ſeems not to know the difference between a negation, and a privation, as any Scioliſt, will gather from his words, <hi>Divin. Phil. p.</hi> 111. <hi>It cannot ſo much as be pretended, that every ſin is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly privative; for every privation preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a habit, which every ſin cannot doe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man may be covetous, or cruell, who never was liberall, or compaſſionate, which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther implies a negation, than a Privation of thoſe virtues which he hath not loſt, but never had:</hi> This is one of the <hi>convincing demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he tells me I had not the courage to venture upon.</hi> Muſt not he be very ſpleen bound, that would not ſmile at ſuch ſtuffe?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33604:57"/> Did this diſputant never peep into a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, to know the ſignification of the word privation? if he did not, why doth he venture to uſe a Philoſophicall dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect? If he did, how could he make ſhift, not to remember, that privation is as well the abſence of a form that ſhould, or might have been in the ſubject, as of a form that ſometime was in it? One of the three principles of naturall generation, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the abſence of a form that never was in the ſubject, but of which the ſubject is onely capable, and yet ſure it was wont to be called <hi>privatio:</hi> But the reader hath had too too much of theſe trifles: I had rather that he would take notice that there is a twofold privation, in reſpect of a habit: The one <hi>pure,</hi> the other not <hi>pure,</hi> the one <hi>in privari,</hi> the other <hi>in privatum eſſe,</hi> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> doth expreſſe it ſomewhat more roundly. The privation alſo which hath reſpect to an action is twofold, one that altogether takes away the act, the other that takes away but the rectitude of the act: the queſtion therefore is; <hi>Whether that evil quality, or</hi> quaſi <hi>quality, from which any act, or habit is denominated evil, be a privation, as I ſay, or a poſitive entity as Mr.</hi> P, <hi>ſaith.</hi> That it is not a poſitive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33604:58"/> I proove by good authority, &amp; better reaſons. By authority, 1. of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and other ancient Chriſtian writers, who did not write in the Scholaſticall ſtile and ſtrain: they with one mouth aſſert the meer privative nature of ſin. <hi>Dionyſ. Areop.</hi> in his book <hi>de Divinis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus</hi> frequently ſpeaks to this purpoſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let the Reader per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the whole diſcourſe of that ancient, in that place, with the two Greek Scholiaſts on him:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greg. Nyſſen. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Oratione Catecheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, pag. mihi</hi> 490. <hi>Joan. Damaſcenus: Orthod. fid. lib.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Greg. Naz. Orat. ad Julianum,</hi> is of the ſame minde. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; his Scholiaſt <hi>Nicetas, p.</hi> 1045. <hi>Neque enim malum ſubſtantia ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33604:58"/> eſt, ſed boni privatio, quemadmodum &amp; tenebrae luminis receſſus: Non enim alia eſt mali ſubſtantia quàm virtutis abſceſſus. Athanaſius</hi> I ſhall commend hereafter. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Latines Auſtin and Anſelm, (who have both, not <hi>obiter,</hi> but <hi>data operâ,</hi> enquired into the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of Sin) have determined it not to be poſitive: <hi>Aug. toto libro de natura boni: Anſelm, de concep. Virg. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>De caſu diaboli, à Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ad</hi> 11. Now though I would not erre with the Fathers, yet do I leſſe diſtruſt my ſelf to erre, while I keep them company, and do with the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, look an adverſary in the face, when my quiver is full of their Teſtimonies: &amp; 'tis in favour to the Readers purſe and patience that I fill it no fuller.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I might ſtrengthen my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from the Schoolmen, amongſt whom I have an Army to a man: as is confeſſed even by <hi>Arriaga.</hi> The firſt that ever was againſt me, as <hi>Faventinus</hi> thinks, was <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan,</hi> and thoſe that aſſert the poſitivity of ſin are by <hi>Rada</hi> called <hi>Cajetaniſtae;</hi> ſo that I may ſay to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> where was your opinion before <hi>Luther?</hi> for <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Cajetan</hi> are known to be contemporaries. Yet not to wrong <hi>Cajetan,</hi> he onely holds
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33604:59"/> the eſſence of the ſin of commiſſion to be poſitive, but that the ſinfullneſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was ſo, he never dreamed. Do theſe authorities ſignify nothing with Mr. <hi>P?</hi> hear him: <hi>Pag.</hi> 174. <hi>If either the Schoolmen erre, or were miſtaken, or were never read, who can help it?</hi> I ſee judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment often varieth with intereſt, and things acquire a price, not ſo much for what they are in themſelves, as for what they are relatively to our ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. The Schoolmen's authority is no good money when he ſhould take it; is currant coyne when he ſhould pay it, I muſt needs ſay that the generall ſuffrage of the Schools doth ſignify much to me, in matters where they are not overawed by a Church Canon. But he hath a prettier evaſion than this, <hi>Pag.</hi> 170. <hi>The Jeſuits in waggery did purpoſely propagate many blaſphemies, ariſing from the tenet of uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall reprobation, in Proteſtant parts of the Chriſtian world, that by making them odious, they might fright men from thence into the Church of Rome.</hi> If there be any Jeſuits that do propagate what they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend to be blaſphemy, I ſhould think a fitter name might be given to ſo Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a practice than that of waggery. Who
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33604:59"/> betrayed him into this obſervation? Dr. <hi>Jackſon;</hi> who yet doth not bluntly ſay, <q>that it's the deſigne of the Factours for the Church of Rome to have this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine generally embraced, or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by us; but inſerts theſe words of <hi>Caution,</hi> or at leaſt to have the World believe that it were generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by us:</q> Beſhrew Mr. <hi>Bar:</hi> who put Mr. <hi>P.</hi> upon a neceſſity of reading this Author, if he can make no better uſe of him. The Jeſuits are generally reputed very Politick; but if this be the beſt poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they have, I ſhould think we need not much fear their plots: For what if they ſhould faſten the Doctrine of abſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation upon the Church of England: <q>Why thence it would follow that the God of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were worſe than an incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Devil, yea thou any wicked Spirit, or the Devil himſelf can without ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be ſuppoſed to be:</q> But doth he not think that men would enquire, whether that frightfull concluſion were rightly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the former principle, would they not tell thoſe Popiſh factours that their Paſtours teach them to confeſſe their ſins, and to take the ſhame of them to themſelves? Would they not bid them
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33604:60"/> dwell at home, and take notice of their own Dominicans, who as ſtrenuouſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the Doctrine of abſolute reprobation as any that go by the name of Calviniſts: the ſame Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3012. <q>He that would diligently peruſe <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> his writings, and in particular his reſolution of that Queſtion, <hi>An detur cauſa praedeſtinationis,</hi> may finde him as ſtrait lace't as <hi>Calvin</hi> was; one and the ſame girdle would be an equall &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meaſure for both their errors: <hi>Nay the Dr. ſaith the</hi> Dominican's and other Schoolmen were more faulty than <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> or his followers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Doctor <hi>Twiſſe, is worſe than the Jeſuit's, though the Jeſuit's and Dominican's are too bad,</hi> Pag. 170. Let me adde that two Papiſts as learned as ever did engage for upholding the Popiſh cauſe, do acquit us of this imputation the making of God the Author of ſin, <hi>Suarez opus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 111. <hi>The Hereticks (poteſtants) know well that God intendeth not that which is formall in ſin, nor inclineth the will of man to intend it.</hi> Vaſquez, diſ. 99. cap. 4. n. 22. Calvin, Zuinglius, Beza, <hi>do plainly affirm that ſin as ſin is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to God as the cauſe thereof,</hi> both
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33604:60"/> theſe Teſtimonies I take upon truſt from <hi>D. F. Wh. P.</hi> 145. Having not the books themſelves by me at the preſent. But to requite him for this obſervation out of Dr. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> who attempts not the proof of it by any one example, I ſhall give him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: That the Popiſh Prieſts will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times go over to the Lutherans and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a converſion, whereas their deſigne is onely to blow up the coals of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt them and the Calviniſts: And at the managing of ſuch a deſigne I am ſure Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath as good a faculty as any man alive. What ſucceſſe can Mr. <hi>Duree,</hi> expect in his negociations for peace, when as men of bitter Spirits from among our ſelves, do not ſtick to make the opinions of the Calviniſts worſe then thoſe of the Atheiſts; And that the Arminians are the conſin-germanes to the Jeſuits, and do underhand aime at the introducing of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, I ſhall give him the opinion of the whole houſe of Commons, whoſe word's in a Declaration of theirs to his Majeſty, are, <hi>The hearts of your ſubjects are perplexed, when with ſorrow they behold a dayly growth and ſpreading of the faction of the Arimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, that being, as your Majeſty well knows, but a cunning way to bring in Popery, and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33604:61"/> Profeſſors of thoſe opinions, the common di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the Proteſtant Churches, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary's of thoſe ſtates in which they have gotten any head, being Proteſtants in ſhew, but Jeſuit's in opinion and practice.</hi> Vid. a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary introduction to the Archbiſh: tryall by Mr. <hi>Prinne.</hi> If he except againſt the houſe of Commons, let him learn the ſame from a Jeſuit's letter to the Rector at <hi>Bruxells.</hi> Father Rector, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>We have now many ſtrings to our bowes, and have ſtrongly fortify'd our faction, and have added two Bulwarkes more; for when <hi>K. James</hi> lived, we know he was very violent againſt Arminianiſme, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with his peſtilent wit, and deep learning, our ſtrong deſignes in Holland, now we have planted the ſoveraigne drug Arminianiſme, which we hope will purge the Proteſtants from their hereſy.</q> This letter was ſeized in the Archbiſh: Study, and atteſted againſt him at the Lords bar: If yet there be not witneſſe enough, wee'l call in the Lord <hi>Falklands</hi> ſpeech, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <q>As Sir <hi>Tho. Moor</hi> ſayes of the Caſuiſts, their buſineſſe was not to keep men from ſinning but to inform them <hi>quam prope ad peccatum ſine peccato liceat accedere;</hi> ſo it ſeemed their worke was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33604:61"/> to try how much of a Papiſt might be brought in without Popery, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy as much as they could of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, without bringing themſelves into danger of being deſtroyed by the Law: Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> to go yet further, ſome of them have ſo induſtriouſly laboured, to deduce themſelves from Rome, that they have given great ſuſpicion, that in gratitude they deſire to return thither, or at leaſt, to meet it half way: Some have evidently laboured to bring in an Engliſh, though not a Roman Popery: I mean not the outſide onely and dreſſe of it, but equally abſolute, a blind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of the people upon the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and of the Clergy upon themſelves: And have oppoſed Papacy beyond the Sea, that they might ſetle one beyond the water: Nay common fame is more than ordinarily falſe, if none of them have found a way to reconcile the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of Rome to the preferments of England, be ſo abſolutely, directly, and cordially Papiſts, that it is all that 1500. <hi>per annum</hi> can do to keep them from confeſſing it.</q> Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> in a Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Univerſity preached at St. <hi>Peters,</hi> on Eaſterday, 1615. <q>Men under pretence
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33604:62"/> of truth, and preaching againſt the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan's, ſtrike at the heart and root of faith and Religion now eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. This preaching againſt the Puritan's, was but the practice of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>Campian's</hi> counſell, when they came into England to ſeduce young Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and when many of them were afraid to loſe their places, if they ſhould profeſſedly be thus, the counſell they then gave them was, that they ſhould ſpeak freely againſt the Puritan's, and that ſhould ſuffice: And they cannot pretend they are accounted Papiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſpeak againſt the Puritan's; but becauſe they are Papiſts indeed they ſpeak not againſt them. If they do at any time ſpeak againſt the Papiſts, they do beat a litle upon the buſh, and that ſoftly too, for fear of troubling or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting the birds which are in it. They ſpeak of nothing but that in which one Papiſt will ſpeak againſt another; as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>aequivocation,</hi> the Popes tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall authority, and the like, and perhaps againſt ſome of their blaſphemous ſpeeches; but in the point of free-will, juſtification, concupiſcence being ſin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> inherent righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33604:62"/> certainty of ſalvation, the Papiſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea can ſay they are wholly theirs, and the Recuſants at home make their braggs of them, and in all things they keep themſelves ſo near the brink, that upon all occaſions they may ſtep o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>From the Doctor of the Chair in <hi>Oxon</hi> I'le lead him to the Univerſity of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> in which I finde a Letter ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unanimouſly by the ſeveral Heads of Colledges, <hi>March</hi> 8. 1595. to their much honoured Chancellor, deſiring from his Lordſhips hands ſome effectual remedy for the ſuppreſſing of <hi>Baro</hi>'s opinions; <hi>Leſt by permitting paſſage to theſe errours, the whole Body of Popery ſhould by little and little break in upon us, to the overthrow of our Religion.</hi> And a little after theſe words doe occurre; <hi>Vouchſafe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips aide and advice both to us (wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, and agreeing in judgement) and all others of the Univerſity ſoundly affected, and to the ſuppreſſion in time, not onely, of theſe errours, but even of groſs Popery, like by ſuch means in time eaſily to creep in among us, as we find by late experience it hath dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly begun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader will pardon me (who can
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33604:63"/> ſcarce pardon my ſelf) for this excurſion, occaſioned through a deſire to acquaint the world, what our former Worthies did think concerning the ſpirit and deſign of our Engliſh Demonſtrants.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It were no difficult matter to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe about my Theſis, denying the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of ſin with a cloud of witneſſes, from among our Modern Divines; but that I have reaſons more than enough, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, they ſtand but for cyphers in Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s account: <hi>Melancthon,</hi> it may be ſhall bee regarded; let's hear him; He wiſheth that there were ſome one common defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſin, unto which all would ſtand; and, for his own part, declareth in more places than one, that he well approveth the Definition given by <hi>Anſelm,</hi> that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal ſin is, <hi>privatio originalis juſtitiae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitae ineſſe.</hi> Nay, <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 163. hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Argument. <hi>If ſin be not a poſitive entity, then God puniſheth for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> by diſtinguiſhing between <hi>nihil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativum,</hi> and <hi>nihil privativum,</hi> by the ſame token that he calls that convincing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration by no better a name than <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villatio;</hi> hence I hamper him in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma; either <hi>Melancthon</hi>'s judgement is ſomewhat worth, or it is not: if not, why
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33604:63"/> is it made ſo much uſe of by Mr. <hi>P?</hi> If it be, then down falls the poſitivity of ſin. I confeſſe theſe horns are in themſelves ſo blunt, that I am almoſt aſham'd to make any uſe of them; but <hi>ad hominem</hi> they are ſharp enough; for with ſuch a pair he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieth he hath toſſed Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King <hi>James, Div. puri.</hi> p. 8. And yet this deplorable Dilemmatiſt, would needs be dealing again with that incomparable Doctor, quite and clean forgetting what befell the poor Frogge in <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables, that would needs be ſwelling againſt the Oxe, a ſecond, and third time. I now inform him, that the Doctor will meddle no more with him; and indeed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take an Anſwer, would be, <hi>intemperanter abuti &amp; otio &amp; literis,</hi> nothing being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered againſt his Epiſtle, which hath weight enough in it to turne thoſe Scales at <hi>Sedan,</hi> of which <hi>Capellus</hi> ſaith, that they would break with the four hundreth part of a Grain. After ſo many teſtimonies, it may ſeem needleſſe to urge reaſons unto Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who profeſſeth, <hi>Divi. Phil. p.</hi> 100. <hi>That none of his principles appeal to reaſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the judgement of the whole ancient aod modern Church.</hi> If by the whole An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Modern Church, he mean every
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33604:64"/> Learned man that hath in any Age been of the Church, I queſtion whether wee can finde a conſent ſo unanimous in any point, except the twelve Articles of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed: But that ſin is a privation, hath been as generally held as any one thing of this nature. Among the Fathers, I know none of a contrary minde: Some few Schoolmen, as alſo Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> I grant were, in reference to ſins of commiſſion; as to ſins of omiſſion, that they alſo ſhould be poſitive is ſo ſtrange, that I know not whether ever it were aſſerted by any, but <hi>Cerberus,</hi> alias <hi>Champneys,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dukes</hi> the Keeper of the great Ordinary at <hi>Hell</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and (whom I would not joyn with ſuch company) the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond:</hi> Yet wee will alſo contend by Arguments arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had uſed one, <hi>p.</hi> 112. in which becauſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> will have me equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, I ſhall ſuffer it, and his Anſwer to play a little before us.</p>
            <p>
               <q>If ſin, as ſin, be a poſitive entity, then it is a thing in it ſelf good, but ſo it is not, therfore neither is it a poſitive enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q> The conſequence is founded upon a very rational, and commonly received
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33604:64"/> Maxim, that <hi>Ens &amp; bonum convertuntur,</hi> though Mr. <hi>P.</hi> be pleaſed to call this, <hi>The printed Article of Mr. B's unchriſtian Creed,</hi> p. 151. But what doth he anſwer?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That all the force of this argument is onely to prove that ſinne is good;</hi> whereas he that hath but half an eye may ſee, that the deſign of the Argument is to fright Mr. <hi>P.</hi> out of his ſad opinion concerning the poſitivity of ſinne, by bringing him to the grand abſurdity, of ſaying ſinne is good.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſaith, <hi>That a thing priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in one reſpect, is alſo poſitive in another; and every Scioliſt can tell, that the corruption of one thing is the generation of another:</hi> Quorſum haec? If he mean, that the corruption of one thing is formally the generation of another, hee falls into ſo loathſome a contradiction, as would make any <hi>Scioliſts</hi> ſtomack riſe at the naming of it. If he underſtand the Propoſition <hi>in ſenſu concomitantiae,</hi> then it is true, that in the ordinary courſe of nature, the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one thing is the corruption of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the corruption of one thing the generation of another; becauſe the matter cannot exiſt without a form, nor under two diſparate forms: But <hi>quid haec ad Iphicli
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33604:65"/> boves?</hi> How that which is properly, and by intrinſecal denomination privative in one reſpect, ſhould be poſitive in another, falls not as yet under my comprehenſion. His examples will perhaps clear my Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuals; <hi>The darkneſs which God created, was not more privative of the day, than it was poſitive of the night; and that which is privative of life or ſight may be poſitive of death and blindneſs.</hi> If his meaning bee, that from the want of light in the aire wee may as truely ſay it is night, as from the preſence of light wee can ſay it is day, that is a truth but very vulgar, if he would ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hint or hold forth,</hi> that the darkneſſe doth actuate and inform the air <hi>per modum qualitatis poſitivae,</hi> as the light doth, there ſeems to be ſuch a darkneſs upon the face of his own underſtanding, as I had thought till now had not been incident to a man of Academical education. If darkneſſe be a Poſitive Quality, pray tell us to what ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Quality belongs it? 'tis not <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> nor <hi>potentia naturalis,</hi> nor yet is it <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas patibilis,</hi> which never was, nor ever can be ſeen, felt, heard, ſmell't, taſted by any one. He hath not yet made himſelfe noyſome enough, the peccant humour ſtill operates; <hi>A Carneadiſt will be glad to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33604:65"/> an opinion, that Sin is good by call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it</hi> bonum Metaphyſicum, <hi>or</hi> tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentale: If ſo, then Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath deſerved his humble thanks, who beſtows a poſitive Entity on ſin. We poor thick-pated Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, who make it but a privation, ſhall merit none of his favour. <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>muſt be taught, that the adequate ſubject of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicall ſcience is,</hi> Ens quatenus ens, reale illud, non omnimodò poſitivum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus eſt poſitivum. A ſtrange ſentence: Can any thing be directly contained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſubject of Metaphyſicks, which is not poſitive? or can any thing be <hi>unum per ſe</hi> (and ſuch is the object of every ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) which is partly poſitive, and partly privative? but we have more either of his ignorance, or inadvertencie: Bonum <hi>in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicks doth no more ſignifie</hi> good <hi>in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, than</hi> canis <hi>the Star doth ſignifie the Dog which walkes about with four feet.</hi> Bonum <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Engliſh doth ſignifie good, as oppoſed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill; but in Metaphyſicks, no more but</hi> Ens <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ordine ad appetitum. How came Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Metaphyſicks ſo to fall out, that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſhould ſtand in oppoſition? Is it not <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nough that it is oppoſed to Greek, and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atine, and other languages, but it muſt ſo ſtand as the oppoſite term to Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks?
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33604:66"/> I ſee others beſides Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians can ſometimes talk non-ſenſe: But doth not <hi>Bonum,</hi> the affection of <hi>Ens,</hi> if it were to be rendred in Engliſh, ſignifie good as oppoſed to evill? Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſure thinks it doth, and therefore in policy he forbears to Engliſh it, onely in Latine he gives us this deſcription: <hi>Bonum eſt Ens in ordine ad appetitum; and that Sin is ſuch, Mr.</hi> B. <hi>knows by ſad and minutely experience.</hi> What uncharitableneſſe is this, to ſay that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> hath minute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience, that ſin as ſin is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his appetite? <hi>Malum qua malum</hi> is not the object of any rational creatures appetite; Nor can it be the object of the rational appetite any more than <hi>falſum quâ falſum</hi> can be the object of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings aſſent. For a cloſe, he tels us, that <hi>malum morale eſt bonum Metaphyſicum; and if Mr.</hi> B. <hi>aimed at nothing but this, he hath gained nothing.</hi> Yes, he hath gained enough: For who would aſcribe a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendental goodneſſe to moral evill, but one, who hath either loſt all his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, or never had any to loſe. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have made a ſhift to ſwallow ſuch a Camel, wee'll try whether we can fetch it up again. May it therefore pleaſe yo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33604:66"/> to underſtand, that they who deſcribe Metaphyſical goodneſs, <hi>per ordinem ad ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitum,</hi> underſtand it primarily with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Divine will:</hi> And will you make ſin the object of the <hi>Divine will?</hi> But <hi>Suarez</hi> will tell you, that good is not ſo compared to the <hi>appetite</hi> as truth is to the <hi>intellect:</hi> for Metaphyſical truth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in its formall nature and denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſome conformity to the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but ſo doth not goodneſs include a conformity to the appetite, though ſuch a conformity be a neceſſary conſequent of goodneſſe. A thing is not therefore good, becauſe deſired, but it is therefore deſired becauſe good. Hence they expreſſe the nature of good by the word <hi>perfectum,</hi> and <hi>conveniens alicui;</hi> and let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> if he can, tell me how ſinne bonificates any ſubject, or addes any perfection to that in which it is.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument uſed by me in the Letter, was to this effect: <q>If ſin be a poſitive Entity, then it is either God, or from God;</q> but it can be neither: <hi>ergo, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetane</hi> found himſelf ſo hard beſet with this Argument, that he ventured to ſay, God was the Author of <hi>malum morale,</hi> but not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33604:67"/> of <hi>malum ſimpliciter ſic dictum:</hi> For the abſurditie of which diſtinction he is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſchooled by <hi>Suarez</hi> in more places than one; but Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath an art worth twenty of the Cardinals diſtinctions, he hath alwaies a whole flood of vilifying words at command; and if he meet with a hard and ſtubborn Argument, he ſoakes it in that liquor ſo long, till the leſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Reader forget that ever any ſuch Argument was uſed. What Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines he rowled up together to keep my Argument from being ſeen, I before ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: I will now take notice of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting pang, with which he ſeems to be ſurpriſed in the height of his perſecutions againſt my Argument: Obſerve how it works, pag. 156. <hi>He muſt know that there is a medium betwixt God and his creatures, and I wonder what ſhould aile him, that he ſhould ſay there is none.</hi> Nay, if I muſt, there is no remedy; but till he have more authority over me, than I yet conceive him to have, I ſhall without fear give him my reaſons, why I neither doe, nor can acknowledge any <hi>medium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe I finde thoſe that had to doe with the <hi>Manichees,</hi> and heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, building their Argument upon
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33604:67"/> this Baſis, that <hi>Omne ens eſt vel primum, vel à primo;</hi> and that <hi>malum</hi> is therefore not cauſed by God, becauſe it is not <hi>ens,</hi> but <hi>non ens,</hi> as they commonly call that which is but a privation: <hi>e: g: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Orat. contra gentes,</hi> p. 6. <hi>&amp; De: incar. verbi,</hi> p. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Greg. Nyſ. Tom.</hi> 2. 490. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. Who is ſuch a ſtranger to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that hath not read ſuch ſentences as theſe from him, <hi>de lib. arbit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Credimus, ex uno Deo, eſſe omnia quae ſunt, &amp; tamen non eſſe peccatorum auctorem Deum? in</hi> 1 cap.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33604:68"/> Joh. v. 1. <hi>Peccatum quidem non per ipſum factum eſt, quia peccatum nihil eſt. Mali author non eſt qui omnium quae ſunt author eſt: quia in quantum ſunt, in tantum bon<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſunt:</hi> 83 <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> It would be endleſſe to put together all ſayings of the Ancients that are of this nature. I ſhall take off my Pen when I have only tranſcribed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable determination of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>, q. 79. ar. 2. <hi>in corpo: actus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>peccati &amp; eſt ens &amp; eſt actus, &amp; ex utroque habet quod ſit adeo: omne enim ens quocunque mod<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſit oportet quod derivetur a primo ente-omnis autem actio cauſatur ab aliquo exiſtente in actu, quia nihil agit, niſi ſecundum quod eſt actu; omne autem ens actu reducitur ad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum actum. ſc. Deum ſicut in cauſam qu<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> eſt per ſuam eſſentiam actus: unde relinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quod Deus ſit cauſa omnis actionis in quantum eſt actio; peccatum nominat ens &amp; actionem cum quodam defectu. Defectus autem ille eſt ex cauſâ creatâ ſc: libero arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio in quantum deficit ab ordine primi agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, i. e. Dei, unde defectus iſte non reducitur in Deum ſicut in cauſam; ſed in liberum arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium, ſicut defectus claudicationis reduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in tibiam curvam, ſicut in cauſam, no<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> autem in virtutem motiva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: a qua tamen cauſa tur quicquid eſt motionis in claudicatione, &amp; ſecundum hoc Deus eſt cauſa actus peccati
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33604:68"/> non tamen eſt cauſa peccati, quia non eſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus quod actus ſit cum defectu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor ſecondly, do I know any other way of defining what <hi>ens primum</hi> is, but this that it is ſuch a being, which is not from any other being, and which is the cauſe of all the beings that are. Thirdly, this poſitive being of ſin is it a finite and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate being? If not, how is it not God? if? How is it not from the Fountain of all eſſences? Fourthly, I am the more confirmed that ther's no <hi>medium</hi> betwixt <hi>Deus &amp; creatura,</hi> becauſe Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all his enquiry hath not been able to finde any. For whereas he doth tell me that the works of the Devill are a <hi>medium,</hi> he could not ſure but think that I would diſtinguiſh in blaſphemy, lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>vital act</hi> and it's deficiency and diſſonance from the Law of God, the act it ſelf I hold to bee poſitive, and from God; the irregularity of that act from which it is denominated blaſphemy, lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would derive onely from mans corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and the Devills temptation. If he will not take this from me, let him take it from thoſe Gamaliels, at whoſe feet he'el not account it any diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſit as a diſciple. Dr. <hi>Fr.</hi> White,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33604:69"/> 
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 104. <q>Defence of his Brother, whereas ſin is a deficience and aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the rule of juſtice, it cannot ſubſiſt alone; but even as halting muſt neceſſarily be joyned with ſome motion of the body, &amp; hoarſneſſe of ſpeech with the action of ſpeaking, ſo the evill of ſin is conjoyned with ſome action, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soul, or body which hath a naturall and poſitive being, and where unto there hapneth a going aſtray from Divine Law, even as it hapneth to a lame mans naturall motion, to have halting concurring with it. Of that which is poſitive &amp; naturall in ſinfull actions Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines acknowledge God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor both in that he perſerveth mans will and faculties, whereby he is ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to his operations, and alſo becauſe as the firſt cauſe he produceth together with the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. cauſe all poſitive motion. Dr. <hi>Sand.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.5. <hi>Ser. Ad pop.</hi> there is a naturall (or rather tranſcendentall) goodneſſe, <hi>honitas entis,</hi> as they call it, in every action even in that where to the greateſt ſin adhereth, and that goodneſſe is from God, as that action is his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the evill that cleaveth unto it is wholy from the default of the perſon
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33604:69"/> that commiteth it and not at all from God, Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> anſwer to Biſhop, <hi>Pag.</hi> 124. We ſay, and you will ſay no leſſe that God is the Author of all the actions in the World, yet we ſay that ſin is wholly and onely of man himſelf. diſtinguiſh the accident from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the ſin of the action from the action it ſelf, God in the one ſhall be glorified &amp; man juſtly condemned for the other.</q> Nay what if M. <hi>Pierce,</hi> himſelf ſay that the ſinfull action, ſo far as it is an action, is from God? He ſaith that every good action of man is from the ſpecial grace of God. Now ſeeing all the good actions that are done <hi>per gratiam viatoris</hi> be and muſt neceſſarily be on ſome account ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; concerning theſe actions I demand are they from God? If not, how is every good action from God? If they be, then he ſpits in the face of his judicious Dr. <hi>Jack.</hi> who ſaith exact: <hi>Col. p.</hi> 3013. <hi>To imagine there ſhould be one cauſe of the act and another of his obliquity, or ſinfullneſſe of the act would be as groſſe a ſolaeciſme, as to a aſſigne, or ſeek after any other cauſe of the rotundity of a ſphere, or bullet beſides him that frames the one, or moulds the other,</hi> or elſe he muſt ſay that the action, &amp; that in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33604:70"/> perfect morall goodneſſe which is in it are from God but the ſinfull imperfection it ſelf is from man through Gods permiſſion, and this he doth ſay 172. But then he ought not to be offended if we take the ſame liberty, <hi>Pag.</hi> 158. He ſaith <hi>God made idolaters men. And</hi> 159. <hi>men themſelves are the works of God onely,</hi> which is to grant more then with truth can be granted. But thus I argue, if God be the cauſe of men, than of <hi>Davids</hi> child begotten by the action of Adultery, for Scripture will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to call that child, ſo ſoon as borne, a man, <hi>John.</hi> 16.21. If the cauſe of that child, undoubtedly then the cauſe of the action of generation by which, as by a cauſality, that child was produced. Yet was he not the cauſe of the adulterious pravity cleaving unto that action. <hi>Quid mirum ſi dicaemus, deum facere ſingulas actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quae fiunt malâ voluntate, cum fate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur eum facere ſingulas ſubſtantias quae fiunt injuſtâ voluntate &amp; in honeſt â actione, Anſ. de caſu diab. c.</hi> 10. So that we are but where we were at the firſt ſetting out. For the actions in which the evill of ſin is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, I'le grant to be poſitive, but from God as well as the creature; the evill of ſin from which they are denominated ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33604:70"/> is but a privation and requireth no proper efficient cauſe at all, ſuch as it hath man is and not God. But I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed his good nature in working, <hi>Pag.</hi> 157. He goes on further to tell me that <hi>res in Metaphyſicks hath three acceptions, in the firſt of wich it comprehendeth entia ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, as oppoſed to nihil.</hi> Before he tell what the other two acceptions are, he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects himſelf, <hi>my deſign is to convert and not confound him,</hi> this charity (as is more than probable) did both begin and end at home had any benefit been intended to me by it, you ſhould have ceaſed ſooner. For I was confunded before that politick <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was made. For let any one tell mee how this diſcourſe about <hi>ens rationis</hi> is here brought in: Firſt, was it to let the World underſtand, that our Author knew what <hi>ens rationis</hi> meant? That's but a low deſign, and yet he cannot accompliſh it neither, for he placeth the model of an houſe to be built hereafter among <hi>entia ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis,</hi> &amp; yet that is as far from being onely <hi>objective in intellectu,</hi> from not being lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than it is thought on, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. Secondly, hath he a mind to inſinuate that ſin is <hi>ens rationis,</hi> if ſo, it muſt either be <hi>privatio,</hi> which is that he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33604:71"/> all along denieth, or a negation, againſt which his arguments militate with more ſtrength, or <hi>a relatio rationis,</hi> which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> but againſt all good reaſons, as I ſhall ſoon ſhew him if forced to ſo great ſeverity by his owning ſuch a paradox. Thirdly, was it his buſineſſe to intimate that all the <hi>entia rationis</hi> are ſo the works of men, as that God cannot be termed the cauſe of thoſe actions, by which they are made? I will not torture his <hi>ingeniolum</hi> with that perplexed que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether the Divine intellect do fabricate <hi>ens rationis,</hi> but without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, the action of the underſtanding, though not the imperfection is from God, are not all our <hi>notiones:</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. in Logick, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia rationis,</hi> yet is the act of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, cauſing them ſo far from not being from God, that God hath indeed a more than ordinary &amp; common concourſe to it.</p>
            <p>The privative nature of ſin may be thus further evicted. <q>If a thing be therefore ſinfull becauſe it wants ſome perfection that it ought to have, and ceaſe to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful when it hath all the perfection which it ought to have, than is ſin a privation; but a thing is therefore ſinfull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Ergo, the conſequence of the propoſition is as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33604:71"/> clear as the noone day light, the aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption alſo needs rather explication than confirmation, ther's not a novice but knows the old rule, <hi>bonum ex integrâ cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſâ, malum ex quolibet defectu.</hi> To make an action good there muſt be a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all the three goods, object, end, circumſtances, the mere want of any of theſe three makes the action ſinfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law requires that all the three goodneſſes ſhould be in the action, &amp; the want of that which the Law requires to to be in any ſubject is a ſin: or elſe we muſt reject, not onely <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but the Apoſtle, who ſaith; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This argument is uſed by <hi>Greg. Arim.</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ancient Schoolman, and largely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon by <hi>Faventinus,</hi> the moſt acute <hi>Scotiſt.</hi> I'me not ignorant that various re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies are made to the argument; but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers alſo are commonly given to thoſe replies, which to tranſcribe would be a matter of more trouble than profit.</p>
            <p>My fourth and laſt argument againſt the pretended poſitivity of ſin I diſpoſe in this <hi>enthymem,</hi> Original ſin is not poſitive, ergo, ſin as ſin is not poſitive. The conſequent (I conceive) will be yeelded <hi>ſine ſanguine &amp; ſudore,</hi> otherwiſe the old Canon, <hi>a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33604:72"/> quatenus ad omne valet conſequentia,</hi> would ſoon command it, as to the antecedent. I deny not but our Proteſtant Divines in their diſputes againſt the Papiſts, doe make a poſitive, as wel as a privative part of original ſin; but how that terme may be underſtood ſo as not to prejudice my aſſertion in the leaſt is largely ſhewed by <hi>Gisber. Voetius,</hi> in his accurate diſcourſe <hi>de propagatione peccati originalis. He that calls it a privation of Gods image, ſaith the whole nature of it,</hi> is a ſentence <hi>of Mr.</hi> John Calvin. That I may prove original ſin not to be poſitive in the ſenſe we now uſe the word poſitive, I muſt lay down this as <hi>a poſtulatum.</hi> That the ſoul is not by propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or <hi>ex traduce,</hi> (as they ſpeak) but immediately created by God. If this <hi>poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum</hi> ſhould not be granted me, I ſhould not fear the demonſtrating of it by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture, and ſtrength of reaſon, to any gain ſayer; but ſuch my charity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids mee to think Mr. <hi>P.</hi> This ſuppoſed, I thus argue. If original ſin be a thing po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, 'tis either the ſoul it ſelf, or ſome of its faculties, or ſome accident or adiunct a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greing immediately to the faculties, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly to the ſoul it ſelf, but none of all theſe; ergo. To ſay with <hi>Flaccius Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:33604:72"/> that it is the ſoule it ſelf, were with more than heatheniſh impiety to calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate the goodneſſe of our Creator, and the like abſurditie will follow if we aſſert it to be one of the faculties of the ſoul. If we ſay it is an accident inhering in the faculties of the ſoul, then it was either put into them by God, which will make God the Author of the worſt of ſins, or elſe it is cauſed in them by the ſouls preſence in, and union to the body, or from ſome action of the ſoul it ſelf: Not by any action of the ſoul it ſelf for it's faculties are ſinfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it put forth any one act of reaſon: Not from its preſence in, or union to the body: for who can imagine how the ſoul, which is ſpiritual and immaterial, ſhould be defiled by being joyned to a body? which though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of naturall imperfections is not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and if it were ſinfull could nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate its ſinfullneſſe to the ſoule that informes it. But now holding origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin to be a privation in an active ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, we do avoid all theſe inconveniences, by ſaying, that Adam by his firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion did ſin away the image of God from himſelf, and his poſterity, who were in him, not onely as a <hi>naiurall,</hi> but as a <hi>federal head</hi> alſo, and ſo God createth
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33604:73"/> the ſouls of men void of his image, and yet juſtly looks on them as ſinners, for wanting this image, becauſe they ought to have it, and by their own folly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themſelves of it.</p>
            <p>As for the reaſons Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath againſt the privative nature of ſin, he hath ſo ſlipt &amp; glided them into all the ſeverall parts of his book, that it is allmoſt impoſſible, to refute them without committing as many <hi>tavtologies,</hi> as he uſeth himſelf in making them, I muſt therefore fall a picking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up, like ſo many dayſies in a bare common, here and there one where I can find them; but firſt me thinks 'tis ſomewhat ſtrange, that my aggreſſor ſhould put forth a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe tending to prove the poſitivity of ſin, and never conſult the Schoolemen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom the queſtion hath been for many years agitated, or if he did conſult them, then it is more ſtrange that he ſhould not find ingenuity to acknowledge whence he borrowed his arguments, and take notice of the ſolutions, ſo commonly and plainly given to them: Yet I confeſſe, ſometimes our diſputant hath let fall ſuch reaſons, as were never thought on by any before him, this is the happineſſe, or rather, unhappineſſe of ſome, that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33604:73"/> they can uſe and urge ſuch <hi>mediums,</hi> which thoſe with whom they deal had not wit, great, or litle enough to foreſee: ſo I remember I once heard a fellow with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confidence ſtrive to prove, that there was no neceſſity of repentance in order to ſalvation, becauſe <hi>the gifts and callings of God are without repentance;</hi> an argument, I dare ſay, with which the Miniſter never expected to be encountred: will't thou ſee its parallel? look <hi>Pag.</hi> 156. <hi>unleſſe Mr.</hi> Hick. <hi>will embrace the ſuds of a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, he muſt confeſſe that to be poſitive which Chriſt came to deſtroy.</hi> The ſuds of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction! A pretty ſimilitude. But I would faine know whether Mr. <hi>P.</hi> will ſay there be any proper privations? If he ſay there be none, he muſt think of making our freſhmen ſome kind of ſatisfaction, for robbing them of one of their poſt-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments; if he ſay there be any, he muſt either let fall this ſad looſe way of arguing, or elſe ſhew us ſome one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of privation, which Chriſt either did not, or could not have deſtroyed, had he ſo pleaſed, by introducing the oppoſit forme into the ſubject, 'tis ſaid 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. <hi>The laſt Enemy that ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed is death.</hi> Will it hence follow,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33604:74"/> that death is no proper privation? The beſt crowers are not alway the beſt fighters.</p>
            <p>A 2. argument is from habitual ſins, which I confeſſe were a good one had it been well managed; but Mr. <hi>P.</hi> can no more uſe it than young <hi>David</hi> could <hi>Sauls</hi> armour; for marke the letters &amp; ſyllables of the man, <hi>Pag.</hi> 161. <hi>Sins of commiſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riveted in a man by long cuſtome and continuance, are commonly called habitual ſins, ſo then Mr.</hi> H. <hi>cannot but confeſſe that vices are habits, as wel as virtues (there is an habit of drunkenneſs as well as of ſo briety) and that habits are qualities he cannot be ignorant if he is but able to tell his fingers; and that a habit is a thing poſitive his poſt predicaments have taught him, where a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and a privation are ſet as oppoſite termes ſuch as do mutually neceſſitate each others abſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What conſequence is this, if I can tell my fingers I can not be ignorant that habits are qualities? Did not Mr. <hi>P.</hi> know how to tell his fingers before he knew that habits were ſpecies of qualitie? Well, but grant him (which is denied by learned <hi>Piccolominee</hi>) that habits are qualities, what's gained? Juſt nothing: he makes a face as if he had intended a <hi>So<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> but
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33604:74"/> hath ſo miſcarried in the purſuance of his <hi>medium,</hi> that I cannot with all my skill mould his words either into a <hi>Sorites,</hi> or any other good forme of argumentation. I ſuppoſe the propoſition <hi>habits are quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> is redundant, and that the thing he aimes at is this, that which is an habit is poſitive, ſome ſins, as drunk. are habits. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, the proof of the Major, becauſe <hi>habit in the poſtpredicaments is ſet as an oppoſite terme to privation.</hi> This would almoſt make a man think, that he took the word <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> to be of as limited a ſignification in the poſtpredicaments as it is in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament, but that is too ſad a failing to charge a Scholar with, yet he falls into one as ſad; for, by making the habit of drunkenneſſe a fit example of habit in the poſtpredicament, he muſt ſet the habit of ſobriety as its oppoſite terme, and make it a privation, which is to cut his own throat: but had his hand been ſoſteddy as that he had hit the marke at which he ſhot, I think he did not take his aime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; for I doubt not whether the habit be poſitive, but whether that vitioſity from which 'tis called an habit of drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be a poſitive entity. How evil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may be ſaid to produce evill habits,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33604:75"/> evill habits produce evill actions, and yet ſin not be poſitive, ſee <hi>Baro. met. de nat. mali.</hi> And to remove prejudice, though he were a Scotchman, yet he was no <hi>Puritan.</hi> Ibid. <hi>There muſt be ſomething poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to make a man poſitively foul, which foulneſſe ſuffers a privation when the man is cleanſed of his filth.</hi> Would not one think that all things conſpire to make the good Rector ridiculous? It muſt indeed be ſome thing poſitive that rendreth the ſinner po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively foul: But how will he prove the filth of ſin to be poſitive? Not from the <hi>Rom.</hi> 22.11. For there be not ſo many Chapters in that Epiſtle; Nor doth he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any other proof: Therefore we may make the ſpiritual filth to conſiſt in the want of that <hi>nitor gratiae,</hi> which either was, or ſhould have been in the ſoul.</p>
            <p>His main argument is from <hi>actual ſins as lying, and blaſpheming, and believing that there is no God,</hi> even in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this argument, he ſhews more of the Palme than of the fift. But that he may not have the ſame quarrel with mee that <hi>Fimbria</hi> had with <hi>Scaevola,</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him a day, becauſe he did not <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum telum in ſe recipere</hi> I would give his argument the beſt advantage I can, by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33604:75"/> ſuppoſing his inſtance to be made in the very worſt, and moſt intrinſecaly evill of all actions; that of hating God, and will ſhew. 1. Why ſuch acts, are called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecaly and eſſentialy evill. 2. What others have anſwered to this objection. 3. What I conceive is to be anſwered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to truth. Such actions are called intrinſecally evill, both becauſe they are evill antecedently to any poſitive Law, and becauſe they are evill <hi>ex genere, &amp; objecto,</hi> and not meerly through the want of ſome circumſtance: for a Scholar to walke in the night ſeaſon, when by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes he is bound to be within his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge walls, is ſinfull, to walke at a time allowed, in a convenient place, and to a good end, is not ſinfull: but the hating of God is ſuch an action, as no circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, or place can make law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Some to anſwer the objection, do make the <hi>totum complexum, odiſſe Deum, the very determination of the hatred to God,</hi> to be the material part of that ſin, and then the formal part, they make to be the want of conformity in this action to the Law of God, and ſo they labor to ſhew, or rather to feigne, ſome conditions in the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33604:76"/> whereof, ſuch an act is ſeperated from it's pravity: Let the Reader, if he pleaſe to ſatisfie his curioſity, conſult, <hi>Greg. valent.</hi> 2. <hi>Tom. in Tho. diſ.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 9. <hi>puncto</hi> 1. Or, <hi>Bradwardine lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. I recite not their words, becauſe I need not their helpe, and becauſe they ſeem to make impoſſible hypotheſes, as if the hatred of God were produced by God in a ſtone, whereas it cannot be that there ſhould be the hatred of God in a ſtone, which neither hath nor can have any knowledge; nay the beaſts, though they have love and hatred, yet cannot be ſaid to hate God, of whom they have no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or repreſentation. I ſay therefore, that the hating of God is <hi>complexum quid,</hi> and muſt not be ſpoken of, as if it were one, the vital action of hatred, is a thing poſitive, but the undue referring, or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating of that act to ſuch an object which is altogether lovely, that's the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the action, and not poſitive but privative: indeed <hi>omne eſſe morale eſt val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de jejunum &amp; diminutum,</hi> moral good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and evill are rather <hi>modi entium</hi> than <hi>entia,</hi> which made <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> though otherwiſe a very acute Doctor, place them, as I noted before, among
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33604:76"/> 
               <hi>entia rationis.</hi> Yet becauſe it belongs to the Univerſality of the firſt cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce not onely every reall being, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the reall poſitive modifications of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Therefore we ſay, that in good workes, both the workes themſelves, and their rectitude are poſitive, and are from God; in evill workes there are alſo two things conſiderable, the workes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their pravity; the workes themſelves we doubt not are poſitive, and from God, as all other poſitive things; but their pravities adde no new entities to them, but conſiſt in a meer privation; in thoſe things which are to be done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a rule, good conſiſts in a conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to, and convenience with the rule, but evill in a difformity, or diſcrepance from the rule; conformity is poſitive, diffor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is privative. And in this Anſwer I am very much confirmed, by the ſayings of <hi>Anſelm,</hi> and <hi>Twiſſe:</hi> Thus <hi>Anſelm, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conc. Praedeſt. &amp; liberi arbitrii cap.</hi> 1. <hi>God cauſed all things which are done, either with a juſt, or injuſt will, that is, good workes, and evill: in good workes he both cauſeth, that they be, and that they be good; in evill, he onely cauſeth that they be, not that they be evill, adding this reaſon of the difference,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33604:77"/> becauſe to be evill is to be nothing: Dr.</hi> Twiſſe, <hi>vind. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>There is a twofold actual concourſe of God, one of Generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, the other of ſpeciall grace; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of generall influence is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to every action, whether good, or evill; but the concourſe of ſpeciall grace, is onely required to a worke throughly good: every good work therefore needs a twofold help, one of generall influence as it is a work, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of ſpeciall grace as good; but an evill work requires onely the concourſe of generall influence, as it is a work, but that it be evill, no more is required than the denyall of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace: Thomas</hi> ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe, 2 <hi>Senten. diſt.</hi> 37. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>A 5. thing which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would fain have to do the office of an argument is this, if every ſin be privative, than there will be no difference betwixt ſins of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſins of commiſſion, but a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betwixt them, therefore, &amp;c. I ſuppoſe thoſe words, <hi>Pag.</hi> 167. Would if reduced to mood and Figure appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us in ſuch a form, as I have now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, <hi>he makes no difference betwixt not bleſſing and curſing God, betwixt ceaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give almes and grinding the faces of the poor, betwixt not ſaving and killing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33604:77"/> man: Anſw.</hi> Sins of omiſſion and commiſſion are ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed, notwithſtanding they be both made to conſiſt in privation: Omiſſion will be the tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an affirmative precept, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion the trangreſſion of a Negative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. 2ly. They differ in reſpect of their immediate foundation, the <hi>fundamentum proximum</hi> of a ſin of commiſſion is ſome act or habit; but theſe are not the <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta proxima</hi> of a ſin of omiſſion: it vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, that I am forced to inculcate theſe ſo vulgar and obvious things, which none are ignorant of, but thoſe who never learned the <hi>A, B, C.</hi> of Philoſophy. To the ſame Cluſter I may reduce what he hath, <hi>P.</hi> 146. <hi>Murder muſt have ſomething in it of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive to diſtinguiſh it in ſpecie from all other ſins:</hi> But <hi>Scotus in</hi> 2. <hi>diſ.</hi> 35. will tell him that the ſpecifical diſtinction of ſin is taken from the different privation of different recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; <hi>Joh. Rada,</hi> will tell him that there is no reall difference betwixt <hi>Thom.</hi> &amp; him in this: deafneſſe and blindneſſe are priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet ſpeeifically diſtinct, becauſe one is the privation of the power of ſeeing, the other of the power of hearing: But how then are the two extreme vices diſtinguiſhed. <hi>e. g.</hi> Covetouſneſs &amp; prodigality ſeing? they are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33604:78"/> privations but of the ſame habit of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe covetouſneſſe is a privation of liberality, as it puts a man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on honeſt ſpending, prodigality is a priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of liberality as it doth incline a man to avoid ſuperfluous ſpending. Thus I have eked out my adverſaries argument, which was ſomewhat ſhort and ſcanty, this made him ſeek to peece it with a patch of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, for ſo it follows, <hi>ſome are not onely po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively but ſuperlatively evill:</hi> the jeſt lieth in <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>ſuperlative</hi> I am content he ſhould thus uſe his wit with out any ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val: But I have been told that ſome years ſince there was one <hi>T. P.</hi> lived near the Schools, who would have made ſuch clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with him and given him 3. for one.</p>
            <p>A 6. argument that he will needs preſſe to fight for the poſitivity of ſin is taken from thoſe Scriptures, which do ſpeak of greater and leſſer ſins, <hi>Pag.</hi> 163. At this I would ſtrike with my Anſwer, if I could find where the veine of proof did lye; if I may gheſſe it lyes in this, that there can be no degrees in a privation, but this is a meer miſtake: Among privations ſome are greater, ſome leſſe, with relation to that forme unto which they are oppoſed: if the forme have degrees of intention,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33604:78"/> that may <hi>Phyſically</hi> be accounted the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter privation which removes more degrees of the Form from the Subject; that the leſſe which removes fewer: if we reckon <hi>morally,</hi> then we may alſo calculate the degrees of privation from the greater or leſſe obligation, that the ſubject is under, to have that form, which for the preſent he wants.</p>
            <p>A. 7. <hi>If ſinne be a privation, how are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and operations aſcribed to it? How doth the Apoſtle ſay ſinne wrought in him all manner of concupiſcence?</hi> Rom. 7.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In ſuch ſpeeches ſin ſignifies not abſtractly and formally; but it ſignifies our nature and its faculties as under corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The faculties in which the ſinfull privations are, by reaſon of thoſe privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe luſt againſt the working of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And now I might take my leave of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> but that I am told of no leſſe than 17 cogent Arguments uſed by him in his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Philanthropie,</hi> which I had not the courage to venture on. When Mr. <hi>B.</hi> told him, that he durſt not quote the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Confeſſion, he is made a lyar for that ſpeech: If he deſerve ſuch a cenſure, ſo I am ſure doth Mr. <hi>P.</hi> How could I be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33604:79"/> ſaid to want courage to meddle with that which I had never read over? And which now that I have been forced to read over, hath rather exerciſed my patience than my courage; ſo far am I from looking upon them as convincing Demonſtrations, that I think I ſhould honour them ſufficiently, if I but ſay that they are good enough for a Sophiſter to uſe when he is put to courſe in the Horſe-fair, <hi>ex tempore.</hi> He ptetends to have proved in ample manner, That ſinne hath an efficient cauſe, properly ſo call'd, being angry it ſeems with the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that makes it to have a <hi>deficient,</hi> rather than an <hi>efficient,</hi> properly ſo call'd. <hi>Pag.</hi> 145. <hi>If man be not the efficient cauſe</hi> (ſaith our doughty Diſputant) <hi>then he is either the material, or formal, or final.</hi> Rather than we will ſeem to be too much frighted, we will ſay that man is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, or ſubjective cauſe of the action; ſuch a material or ſubjective cauſe as evill can have: And he is the efficient cauſe too of the evil of the action, if by an effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient he meane no more than that unto which it may be aſcribed. But he and I both were beſt not to make too much noiſe, leaſt wee ſhould awaken the youngſters to fall aboard us with ſuch an Argument as
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33604:79"/> this. If man be the efficient cauſe either of a good action or a bad action, then hee doth effect it by another action, and ſo we may proceed <hi>in infinitum.</hi> To let that paſs: the deficient cauſe is reduceable to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; and this is to be ſaid; Suppoſe the firſt ſin of Angels to have been a proud deſire to be equal unto God; the cauſe of this proud deſire was the will of the Angel; but it was the cauſe of the action (in ſuch a ſenſe as a cauſality may be ſaid to have a cauſe) <hi>per ſe,</hi> of the vitioſity of the action, it was onely the cauſe <hi>per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, &amp; per concomitantiam;</hi> nor doth the vitiotſiy of the effect alway ſuppoſe a viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity in the cauſe; though it alway pre-ſuppoſeth an imperfection in the cauſe; and where the cauſe it ſelf is vitious, its vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſity is not the cauſe of the vitioſity of the effect; for vitioſity of it ſelf, neither can effect, nor be effected; but the vitious cauſe, taking together the being, and the ſupervenient privation, is the cauſe of the vitious effect, taking it in like manner for the beeing, and the ſuperadded privation. But if we contradict him, we muſt ſay, that God damns men for nothing. <hi>Anſelm,</hi> in the place I before referred my Reader to, makes this objection, and laugheth at
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33604:80"/> its, weakneſſe, <hi>De Con. vir. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Quidam cum audiunt peccatum nihil eſſe ſolent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: ſi peccatum nihil eſt, cur punit Deus hominem pro peccato, cum pro nihilo puniri nemo debeat; quibus quamvis humilis ſit quaeſtio, tamen quia quod quaerunt, ignorant, aliquid reſpondendum eſt.</hi> What doth hee mean when he ſaith, that God then muſt puniſh men for nothing? If he meane that God would puniſh men becauſe they have not that in their faculties, habits, actions which ſhould be in them what abſurdity is there in that? Is not the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment juſt, except it be for poſitive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities? How many men have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for not paying ſummes of money which they did owe? Yea I beleeve Mr. <hi>P.</hi> could well enough bear my being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for not paying him his Arrears which he (vainly enough) fancyeth to bee due to him, and yet non-payment cannot be accounted a poſitive entity; nor doth Mr. <hi>P.</hi> know how to place it in any predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament of Beeings. <hi>Siu is a puniſhment, but puniſhment is a poſitive entity.</hi> erg. There is a puniſhment of loſſe, which ſcarce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any man ſaid was poſitive: There is a puniſhment of ſenſe, and this we ſay is no other way an evil or a puniſhment unto
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33604:80"/> us than as it doth deprive us of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of which we are capable. The puniſhment of ſenſe may be ſaid to be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive as to its foundation, not in its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality; that is, it is not poſitive, if wee conſider that in which the very evill of that puniſhment formally conſiſts. As to the reſt of his Arguments, they are part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as I have met with before, and partly ſuch as others upon whoſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they are grounded, are more concerned in than my ſelfe. When Mr. <hi>P.</hi> will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to vindicate every expreſſion that hath been uſed in the managing of theſe controverſies by men of his opinion, then may I perhaps ſenſe ſome kind of obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to try whether I can juſtifie every thing that hath fell from Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in the mean time they are of age, let them ſpeak for themſelves, if they count it needfull: if they count it not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, why ſhould I ſpend labour about that, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the doing of which I cannot take any great pleaſure, and for the doing of which <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey will con me no great thanks. This I <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot but obſerve, that though none durſt undertake Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> in the Arminian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roverſies, whileſt he was alive, yet ſince his death every puny will be nibling at
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33604:81"/> him upon all occaſions, which puts me in minde of that paltry fellow in <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> who being never able to get the maſtery in his life time of one <hi>Theagenes</hi> a famous Wreſtler, came many a night after hee was dead and ſcourged his Statue, which was erected in the honour of him. <hi>Pauſ. in Attic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>T. P.</hi> or Mr. <hi>I. G.</hi> doe verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> to be an enemy of that Divine grace, which he pretends to have maintained, let them follow him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he did thoſe with whom hee tooke occaſion to deale; and when they ſhall have ſo done, <hi>Mr. Jeanes,</hi> a perſon of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcholaſtical head, will not long let them be without an anſwer. And ſo I leave my Combatant, reſolving, if it may be, never more to come ſo near him, till I am told by others, that his breath ſmels ſweeter.</p>
            <p>Upon the review of my book J cannot but recal what <hi>I</hi> have often read from <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Cognatus,</hi> of a man with an ulcer in his face, who paſſing over a Bridge where the paſſengers were to pay a certaine piece of mony for every malady of body found upon them, was required to pay the accuſtomed tribute for the ulcer in his face; but hee refuſing to pay it, the Officer pulls off his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33604:81"/> hat, intending to keep it for a pawn; his hat being taken off, another malady appears in his bald head. Now Sir (ſaith the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer) I muſt have a double tribute of you; Nay (ſaith the Traveller) that you ſhall not, and begins to ſtrugle with the Officer; who being too ſtrong for him, gave him a foyl, by means whereof there was a rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture perceived under his coat: Now (ſaith the Officer to him againe) <hi>I</hi> muſt have a treble tribute of you. The more <hi>Mr. P.</hi> doth ſtruggle, the more doth he diſcover his infirmities; yet I beleeve he will not be quiet; for they that have a bad cauſe will alway have the laſt word, if death doe not ſtop their mouthes. But as to my ſelf, I think we had both been held wiſer men if we had held our peace, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing the heat of theſe Epidemical controverſies hath produced more Writers then (to uſe <hi>Plautus</hi> his ſimilitude) an hot ſummer brings forth buzzing flies; and therefore, though <hi>Mr. P.</hi> through his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking language, hath made a coward to fight for once, yet will he ſcarce draw me into the field again; for neither can I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the judicious tryal of the Learned, nor am I willing to hazard the paſſionate
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33604:82"/> cenſures of the ignorant; nor have I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that many have been healed by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the troubled waters, though mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the beſt Angels of the Church. Truth is ſo lovely, and beautifull, that they who embrace Falſhood, will needs have it to be Truth; and becauſe they are unwilling to be deceived, they will not be convinced that they have been deceived. If <hi>Mr. P.</hi> doe reply ſeriouſly and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, ſo as that I be convinced, it will be ſufficient, that in a private Letter I thank him for undeceiving me, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize him to publiſh to the world, that I am his Proſelyte. But if his Reply ſhall be ſeaſoned with the ſalt of <hi>Momus,</hi> not of <hi>Mercury;</hi> or if it be ſtuffed and coloured onely with an <hi>ignorantia elenchi,</hi> defending that which is not impugned; or if he ſhall like the flyes, ſeek for, and ſtick onely upon a ſore place, fall on the ſick and weak parts of my diſcourſe, and never attempt to charge through the main body, I ſhall vindicate my ſelf only with contempt and ſilence. When a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Nation had a controverſie in Law with a Brewer, who had a Garden and dwelling houſe bordering upon his: The
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33604:82"/> Brewer gave it in charge to his ſervant to put in ſo many hogſheads of water more into all his Brewings, than he was wont to doe, telling him that ſuch a ſupply would bear the charge of his ſuit with his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; which being overheard by the Nobleman, he ſent preſently to the Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, reſolving he would no longer goe to Law with him, who upon ſuch eaſe and cheap termes could manage his part of the ſuit. I neither make my ſelf the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor Mr. <hi>P.</hi> the Brewer, but yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſuffers his fancy to flye abroad ſo faſt, ſeeing he hath a fluid ink-pot, as ready at hand as the <hi>Thames</hi> to the Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; ſeeing he can print more Books in two years, than a wiſer man would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to print in all his life; nay, ſeeing rather than not bee a good cuſtomer to <hi>Mercurius Politicus,</hi> he will clap a new Title to his old Works. I may well be excuſed if I have no mind to meddle fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him. Of all diſtempers I hope I ſhall keep my ſelf free from the itch of diſputing and writing many books: And I doubt not but wiſe men will count it more commendable to ſtand out, than to play at ſmall games.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:33604:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The God of Truth and Love, teach us to follow the truth in love, that we may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33604:83"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
